<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A reply to A vindication of a discourse concerning the unreasonableness of a new separation &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Grascome, Samuel, 1641-1708?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 118 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41815</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1576</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31730</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12248870</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12248870</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57050</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41815)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57050)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1504:32)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A reply to A vindication of a discourse concerning the unreasonableness of a new separation &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Grascome, Samuel, 1641-1708?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCI [1691]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Grascome by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Williams, John, 1636?-1709. --  Vindication of A discourse concerning the unreasonableness of a new separation.</term>
               <term>Stillingfleet, Edward, 1635-1699. --  Discourse concerning the unreasonableness of a new separation.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  History.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57050:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A REPLY TO A Vindication OF A DISCOURSE Concerning the <hi>Unreaſonableneſs of a New Separation,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year M DC XCI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:57050:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:57050:2"/>
            <p>AMONG all the Reformed Churches, none departed from <hi>Rome</hi> with greater Advantage than the Church of <hi>England.</hi> The certain Succeſſion of Authority, as well as purity of Doctrine, and both maintained by Men as famous for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity of their Lives, as Profoundneſs of their Learning, made her for a long time the Glory of the Reſormation, and both the Envy and Terror of her Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries. For this Reaſon ſhe became the principal Mark, at which all Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands were darted; and no Arts were neglected, which might by any means raiſe up Enemies againſt her, till in the former Rebellion, overwhelmed with the Multitude, Malice, and Wickedneſs of her Foes, either her Preiſts, with others, were barbarouſly murdered, or ſhut out from the Temples, and debarr'd from the daily Sacrifice: And <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> it ſelf was made an heap of Stones. But though this did eclipſe her Beauty, and (as ſome thought) well nigh defac'd her, yet ſuch was the Sincerity of her Members, that thoſe bloody Perſecutions did indeed raiſe her Reputation; and made many, who admired their Conſtancy, enquire into thoſe Principles, from whence ſprang ſuch wonderful Effects; whereby ſhe gained no few Proſelytes: And as, when the Heathens, accounting all ſure, ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Statues to <hi>Diccleſian,</hi> with this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, <hi>Superſtitione Chriſti ubi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leta,</hi> the Chriſtian Church ſoon after broke forth with greater Splendor than ever; ſo when our Enemies thought they had raked up that long afflicted Church in Aſhes, on a ſudden, and beyond hopes, ſhe roſe with ſuch a Luſtre as ſtruck Envy dumb, and her Enemies with Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, as ſeeing the Finger of God in it. And thus it might have long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued, had there not been a falling away, and her own Members renounced her Principles. But, alas! now her Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is worſe and more deſperate than ever, unleſs God be her Helper. <hi>Rome</hi> hugs herſelf, and laughs to ſee the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of that Church debauched, and that effected by ſome few Vipers bred in her Bowels, which all their Craft and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry could never bring to paſs. The Diſſenters ſmile and inſult, to ſee the worſt of their Principles taken up, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to have been always Principles of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> And as for thoſe few, whom no Plagues or Penalties can force to abdicate their Mother, and with Rancour vomit up that Divine Food they ſuckt from her Breaſts; whilſt even their Enemies commiſerate them, thoſe who call themſelves their Brethren proſecute them with the utmoſt Malice, as if no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing would ſerve them but <hi>Root and Branch,</hi> and they were fully reſolved to deſtroy that poor diſtreſſed Church, <hi>both Name and Thing:</hi> And unleſs God of his Infinite Mercy prevent their implacable Deſigns, to the eye of Senſe it ſcarce ſeems avoydable.</p>
            <p>Experience may have ſufficiently taught us, That Schiſm not only breeds ill Blood, but worſe Actions; and not only cauſeth Heats and Animoſities, but often raiſeth Men to that Madneſs of Zeal, that they think they do God good Service by the moſt unjuſtiſiable Deeds, and barbarous Immanities; and I pray God that theſe times may not too much feel the Effects of it. Upon this account every good Man will not only Mourn over the Diviſions of <hi>Reuben,</hi> but by all honeſt Means endeavour to allay them: And if I could be convinced, That the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57050:3"/>
Guilt of the preſent Schiſm lay at our Door, I ſhould think it ought to be my firſt Work to Repent of it. And thô the Author I have to do with writes at that rate, as if he intended not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince any Man, but reproach all, who are not of his Party; yet I will paſs that by, and do him the Juſtice to examine whatever may ſeem in the leaſt mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial thorough his whole Diſcourſe, and ſo leave the Judgment to the Impartial Reader.</p>
            <p>For a taſte, at firſt, what awkard doings we muſt expect all along, he anſwers my little Piece backwards, and begins at the end. And becauſe I ſaid I was unwilling to <hi>judge ſeverely of my Brethren,</hi> he thinks he hath no ſmall advantage in picking up three or four harſh Phraſes, which dropt from my Pen: As if a Man could have no kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for others, who ſometimes ſpeaks in ſharp Language, when bitter Truth enforceth him to it, and the Nature of the Thing will not be otherwiſe expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. But this Complaint very ill becomes him, who at every turn, on ſet purpoſe, calls me by all the ſcornful, deſpicable Names, a malicious Wit can invent; and ſometimes gives me ſuch ill-favoured Titles, with Threatning to boot, as if he had a mind to deal by me, as the Heathens with the Primitive Chriſtians, who, when they would expoſe them to be torn in pieces, dreſt them in the Skins of Bears, or other Savage Beaſts. But this I can neglect: For though it may recommend his Book to ſome kind of Wits, yet it will certainly diſparage it with all Men of Senſe.</p>
            <p>My Anſwer contained only two Sheets, ſo that it could be neither difficult nor tedious to have anſwered it as it lay: But, as if he were loſt in a Wood, or had to do with ſome Voluminous Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, he reduceth it to Heads; but as there I followed another Man's Steps, ſo here, to prevent all Complaints of foul play, ſeeing our Author will not allow me my own Method, I will follow his. But firſt, I cannot forbear to tell him, That I do not think that he hath done like an ingenuous Man in theſe things. 1. That he hath quite omitted ſeveral Reaſons of mine, which were material as to the Matter in Controverſy. 2. That when he mentions Topicks, or hints at any of my Arguments, he never repeats thoſe Words wherein the ſtrength of the Argument lay. 3. That he rarely makes any direct Anſwer; but ſhifts and turns it off to another Matter, like ſome crafty Huntſmen, who being deſirous to ſave the life of an old chac'd Hare, and yet to gull thoſe who follow the Sport, and think the ſame Game is ſtill on foot, ſtart, and lay the Dogs into a freſh one. And in theſe three things conſiſts both the Artifice and Strength (if it have any) of his whole Book.</p>
            <p>The firſt Topick he makes to be of <hi>Church-Communion and Schiſme;</hi> and here the firſt Offer he makes is a Side<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blow, in ſtiling us the <hi>New Separatiſts, (p.</hi> 3.) Now Schiſme certainly goes along with the Cauſe; and thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly are the Schiſmaticks who are the Criminals: Now let Matters be firſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſted, and the Cauſe examined, and let thoſe be the new <hi>Separatiſts</hi> who ſhall be found Guilty upon Tryal; and if his new Titles of Honour be not found of Right to belong to himſelf and his Party, I will confeſs that I have been wofully miſtaken.</p>
            <p>That we <hi>do not fall, but are forced in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Diviſion,</hi> I had alledged. This he ſaith he will anſwer in due place, and I muſt wait his Leiſure. But when he calls it a <hi>Spiteful Return,</hi> when I deſire that Author to <hi>ſpeak with more Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of a Caſe of Conſcience,</hi> if he had withal added my Reaſons, it would have plainly appeared that nothing but front<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Impudence would have called that Spitefulneſs. But to divert the Diſcourſe, he tells me, That I have <hi>over-run the Point.</hi> For (ſaith he) <hi>the Word Only is not as if a Caſe of Conſcience was not a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:57050:3"/>
matter of Conſequence; but that the taking or not taking the Oaths, is only a Caſe of Conſcience, not matter of Doctrine.</hi> But doth not the Strength of his Argument lye in this, That the taking or not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Oaths is only a Caſe of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, about which wiſe and good Men may differ? And doth not he by this means endeavour to repreſent it as a Matter of ſmall Moment or Importance? and I think this is not to make it a Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of any great Conſequence. Or do I there ſpeak any thing of Doctrine, but ſtrictly keep my ſelf to the Plea of a Caſe of Conſcience? Was not my prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Reaſon this, That there was not any Moral Action, and conſequently not any Duty of a Chriſtian, about which a Caſe of Conſcience might not at one time or other ariſe? And if theſe may be determined either way, becauſe wiſe and good Men may differ, this will ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſtroy the very nature of Good &amp; Evil, or make the Bounds ſo moveable, that we ſhall never know certainly where to find them. But becauſe theſe and other Reaſons deſerve no Anſwer, let us ſee whether he hath made the matter better or worſe by what he will vouchſafe us. It is only <hi>a Caſe of Conſcience,</hi> (he ſays) <hi>not Matter of Doctrine.</hi> What is the meaning of this? Doth he think practical Caſes things indifferent, and that nothing is of moment but matter of Theory? Provided that a Man doth believe in general that Oaths are obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, is it lawful for him in practice to take contradictory Oaths, and be guilty of Perjury? I confeſs, That I ſhould have a better Opinion of the Quaker, who denies the Lawfulneſs of all Oaths, than of that Man who maintains the Lawfulneſs of Breaking all Oaths: The one may prevent Perjury, the other en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courageth it without end. But if Men put ſuch a Senſe upon promiſſory Oaths, as, contrary to their Nature and Deſign, makes them to be no Security, I leave it to indifferent Perſons to judge, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that Man doth not in effect invali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date all promiſſory Oaths, and ſet up ſuch a Doctrine as teacheth the Lawfulneſs to break them: And I think we need not go far to ſeek Men who do thus. But this Oath (he ſays) is a <hi>Matter of a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Nature.</hi> What then? Is not God appealed to in the taking it? Is not his holy Name profaned, and his Wrath and Vengeance provoked, if it be taken in Violation of former Oaths, <hi>i. e.</hi> in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury? What if its Meaning be to be learnt from the <hi>Conſtitution and Laws of the Realm?</hi> Has it not therefore a certain Senſe and Meaning? And if there be Sin in it, is it not a ſufficient ground to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to communicate in that Sin, or to joyn with perjured Perſons in their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury? But here he ſhameleſly inſinuates, That the Matter of our Difference is only Scruples; when I had told him, as plainly as a Man could ſpeak, That we had no Scruples. If a Man ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage me to murther my Father, or rob him of all he hath, ſhould I make any Scruple to reject the Council of ſuch a Villain? I think there is as little Reaſon for a Man to raiſe Scruples why he may not forſwear himſelf, as why he may not commit Theft, Murther, or Adultery. He ſcarce deſerves the Name of a Chriſtian, who doth not, without any Scruple, condemn theſe Sins.</p>
            <p>After this ſhift, he next puts two Pleas in our Mouths, and then makes two Anſwers for his learned Author. The Firſt Plea is, <hi>That when any Thing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful is made a condition of Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it will juſtify a Separation.</hi> As to which he tells us, his Author made An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>That taking the Oaths is no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Communion with us, and ſhewed that the Terms of our Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are not altered.</hi> This, indeed, he ſaid, but he never ſhewed or proved, nor ever can. For will he ſay, That the matter of the Oaths is not made a condition of Communion to all Men? Are we not obliged to pray for the ſame thing in more ample, plain, and ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant Terms, than we are to ſwear it?
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57050:4"/>
Now whatever Objections we have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Oath, our principal Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is againſt the matter of it, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duely, and unjuſtly aſſigned; and if the Owning and Praying for this be made a part of the daily Office, it is made a condition of our Communion; and if ſo, then the terms of our Communion are altered. And thus he may ſee that a Man may ſooner prove the Oaths to be made conditions of Communion, then tell of forty Things they are not: But this will be done more fully after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
            <p>As to the Second Objection, he tells us his Author ſays, <hi>That it is the Scruple about mix'd Communion, which hath been ſo long exploded among us;</hi> and this he ſays, <hi>I was very careful to paſs over in ſilence:</hi> And perhaps he did not very ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſedly to be my remembrance: For I will not paſs it over ſo now. For ſhould I ſuffer that to lye againſt us, I ſhould expoſe both my ſelf, and others to a ſevere Cenſure. But I have known Boys ſet up a <hi>Daſlin,</hi> and then ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly laugh and tryumph to ſee how bravely they knockt it down again; and when other Men make our Objections for us they may frame them on purpoſe ſo as to faſten on them ſome ridiculous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences, which they had before in their Head; and that indeed may make them Sport, but it doth not affect us: And I cannot think that this Author did believe himſelf, when he caſt this Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny upon us, as think us ſo very Weak and Silly to ſeperate upon the Terms of thoſe Enthuſiaſts, who thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Defiled in mix'd Communions. Had he ſtated the Objection fairly, there had been no colour for his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: But ſince he is reſolved to caſt all Slanders upon us, I ſhall briefly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent our Senſe in this Caſe, which will be ſufficient to wipe them off. We do not ſeperate from them upon the account of any particular Frailties, or any perſonal Infirmities, or Sins. We do not ſeperate from them for that they have taken unlawful Oaths, though we think them bad Men for doing ſo; and worſe for hardening themſelves in their Sin by maintaining them, and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging others to be as bad as themſelves; good Offices may be diſcharged by ill Perſons, if lawfully authorized there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; and where the Terms of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion are Sound, the particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Failings of a Man, in other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, affects not the Communion; both <hi>Judas</hi> and <hi>Demas</hi> may execute their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to the benefit of others, though it were to be wiſhed, that ſcandalous Sins were leſs rife in the World; for a ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Cup is apt to turn the Stomack againſt the moſt wholeſome Liquour; and Devotion is apt to grow chill, when the Offices of the Communion are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged by a Perſon, whoſe ordinary Actions are known to be Wicked, and diſagreeable to his Official Preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but, yet this will not Warrant the violation of Communion. But the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, why we Communicate not with you is, becauſe we cannot do it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being guilty of Sin in ſo doing, which I have already in part proved from theſe two Heads; Firſt, That we are unjuſtly diſcharged from the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of our Office, which we ought not to ſubmit to, but Exerciſe at our Peril, being we cannot do it otherwiſe. Secondly, That there is evil in the very Terms of your Communion; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whether the Oaths be made condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Communion or not, we have ſufficient Ground to refuſe your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; and this I ſhall more fully prove hereafter, as our Author gives me Occaſion; for I am bound to follow a kind of deſultory Wit, which like a <hi>Monkey,</hi> in a drying Room, is always leaping from one Line to another, and though he never ſtays long on the ſame, yet he is never long from it.</p>
            <p>Whereas the Author againſt a New Separation had put this Caſe, <hi>That ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the Swearers to blame, yet if they acted according to their Conſciences, there
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57050:4"/>
could be no reaſon for a Separation, unleſs it be lawful to ſeperate from all, who fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the dictates of an erronious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and ſo there will be no end of Separation;</hi> to which I did reply to this effect, That though we may be bound to ſeperate from ſome erronious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, yet it doth not follow, That we may lawfully ſeperate from all. This he calls <hi>another of my Blunders.</hi> But to prove that we may ſeperate from ſome erronious Conſciences, (and, I think, we ought to ſeperate from no other) and yet Schiſm not be endleſs: I gave this Reaſon, <hi>That all erronious Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences had not an equal influence on Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion and good Manners, ſo that it is not the erronious Conſcience, but the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Thing wherein Conſcience errs, which according as it affects Communions, either requires a Seperation, or allows a continuance of Communion;</hi> and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular inſtances I there propoſed. But as if he were afraid he ſhould burn his Fingers, he never ſaith one Word to his Blunderers Reaſons and Inſtances; and yet to give him his due, he here endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to ſplit the Hair. For he calls me back, and tells me that his Friends ſuppoſition was this, <hi>That though the Swearers were to blame, yet if the Oaths were not made a condition of Communion, there could be no cauſe aſſigned for a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration on that account.</hi> But if I give him this, yet it is plain Force on his part, and to make me agree to his Authors Suppoſal whether I will or no. For it was my Buſineſs to ſhew, That the Suppoſition did not lye in our Caſe; and I there not only aſſerted but proved, That the erronious Conſcience, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which we Diſcourſed, was ſuch as did affect Communion. Now if a Man will always ſay the ſame thing, and conſtantly hold and repeat his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, without any regard to any Arguments offered againſt it, I muſt allow that Man to have this peculiar advantage of all others, That he can never be Confuted.</p>
            <p>I confeſs I did charge his Author, <hi>That he had not fairly ſtated the Caſe;</hi> and, I think ſtill, that it ought not only to have been conſidered, whether the Penalties bore any proportion to the pretended Crime, but whether the Power it ſelf had any lawful Authority either to impoſe the Oaths, or inflict the Penalties? For if that was wanting, than it is certain, That greater Iniquity and Injuſtice could ſcarce be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, then ſuch unlawful Impoſitions, and ſuch mercyleſs Uſage. But here, to be even with me, he tells me, <hi>That it was my Miſtake; for if there be no reaſon for the Scruples about the Oath, there can be no reaſon for their ſake to ſeperate. (p.</hi> 6.) Still he is at his <hi>Scruples,</hi> though in effect I had before told him, That if there be ſuch a thing as Perjury, the Oaths muſt without Scruple be unlawful. But to admit his Reaſoning at preſent, yet if there be Reaſons for Scruple, and the Oaths be unlawful, than the Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are Unjuſt as well as Mercyleſs, and there may be Reaſon to ſeperate on their account; and, I think, this ought to have been conſidered as well as the other, and not ſuch an eaſie ſtate of the Caſe, only propounded, as if there were no more to do, but get up and ride. And yet, after all, as tryumphant as he is, his Conſequence is not univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally Good; for though it is not our Caſe, yet there may be Caſes, wherein an Oath may be either lawfully taken, or lawfully refuſed; and though there be no Scruple in ſuch Caſe, yet a Man's Actions may be Warrantable, ſo far as tending to the Juſt and Honeſt Defence of his Liberty, when ſuch Oaths are impoſed with Unjuſt and Mercyleſs Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties.</p>
            <p>But it ſeems I am guilty of another miſtake; for he tells me, <hi>That if the Oaths are Lawful, the Penalties how <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt and Rigorous ſoever, cannot make them <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful.</hi> But he ought to have conſidered, That I called thoſe Penalties <hi>Mercyleſs,</hi> in reſpect of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57050:5"/>
Diſproportion; and ſuch they might be, though the Oaths were Lawful: But then I ſaid they were <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt,</hi> in reſpect of the Unlawfulneſs of the Oaths them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Now to anſwer this by ſaying, <hi>if the Oaths are Lawful,</hi> is meerly to beg the Queſtion, and to argue upon the Suppoſition of that, as granted, which is the Matter in diſpute.</p>
            <p>He will needs reduce my Arguments to three Heads, of which the firſt he makes this, <hi>That the Penalties to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon us, want nothing of being a condition of Communion to us, quatenùs Miniſters.</hi> Now I thought they had been inflicted already, but if they are to be inſlicted, than it ſeems there are more to come, and I was more in the Right than I was aware, when I called them <hi>Mercyleſs,</hi> for ſo they were with a Witneſs; of which we ſhall know no end, nor from time to time what they ſhall be. To ſecure Uſurpation what in them lies, by endleſs Puniſhments, is to put the Uſurper into the place of God Almighty: For none but he can in Juſtice puniſh without end. I now begin to think, that inſtead of pittying our unjuſt Sufferings, they will inflame what they can, and get thoſe Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties put in Execution, which ſome have threatned, for the Warning againſt which we are more beholden to their Anger than their Honeſty.</p>
            <p>But before he takes notice wherein my Argument pincheth him, he pretends to anſwer what I urged as the <hi>fatal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence</hi> of ſuch Penalties. And here, with a great deal of wit, (as he thinks) he tells me, <hi>That there may be Forty things which may have the ſame fatal Conſequence.</hi> And if what he ſays be true, is it any Anſwer to my Argument? But let us however examine his Inſtances; and he tells us it would have been of the <hi>ſame fatal Conſequence, if the Clergy had not ſubſcribed,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>if they had not declared their Aſſent and Conſent,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>if they had not taken the Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy in former Kings Reigns;</hi> and he might have added, if People ſhould Renounce Chriſtianity, which I fear many are, ſtrongly tempted to, whilſt they hear the Miniſters of it Preach away God's Commandments, and thoſe who ought to be the ſevereſt Enemies of all Wickedneſs, to Canonize Perjury and Injuſtice for Chriſtian Virtues. But to anſwer his particular Inſtances; Will he ſay, That either the things commanded, or the Authority commanding, then was unlawful? If not, how comes it up to our Caſe; or how could they juſtly be made a ground of Separation? But he would not ſee wherein the <hi>Fatality of the Conſequence</hi> I urged lay; which if he had pleaſed to do, he might have ſpared all his Inſtances, though he had had Forty more. Suppoſe the Caſe thus; a Government requires ſomething to be done, which is ſinful and unlawſul, with which if the Clergy will not comply, they ſhall be diſcharged from the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of their Function and Duty. Now in ſuch a caſe, God forbids Compliance; and if they are bound to ſubmit to the Government, and ceaſe from the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of their Miniſtry, upon Non-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance; then it will lye in the Power of the Civil Government, whether God ſhall be worſhipped in the Land or not. For ſin we muſt not; and yet if we muſt acquieſce under the Penalty, for not complying, then it is in their Power to diſcharge every Man from his Duty: And therefore in ſuch a Caſe I ſay we muſt do out Duty at our Peril; we muſt do well, and be content to ſuffer Ill; we have no Remedy in ſuch Caſe, but to bear our Croſs. And to avoid or explode the Doctrine of the Croſs here, were in the conſequence to thruſt Chriſtianity out of the World. Of this not a word; and indeed our Author's great Skill lyes in avoiding, not anſwering, Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>He farther adds, That the Penalties, though great, <hi>are neither unjuſt or mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſs, if the Government is not otherwiſe to <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſecured.</hi> What! not though the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57050:5"/>
thing commanded be Sinful? May a Government then enjoyu Wickedneſs under the ſevereſt Penalties, if it be thought for its Security, and yet be blameleſs? There are a ſort of Men are ſtrangely careful for ſome Governments, and what a ſmall ado is required to eſtabliſh a Throne in Unrighteouſneſs, and after all, it will never be done; but either this will not ſecure the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment according to your Principles, or it may be without it. For I muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate you to remember a common Diſtinction amongſt your ſelves, I mean that <hi>between Government and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours;</hi> and then be pleaſed to call to mind who it is, that expreſly ſays, <hi>That the Oath is to the Government, not to the Perſon.</hi> Now ſuppoſe a Man ſhould take the Oaths with a deſign, at the ſame time, to ſecure the Government, by putting it into other Hands: I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee but that a Man may lawfully do thus upon your Principles; and yet this were to make an Oath the moſt deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Cheat that ever was known, or heard of. Sure the Eyes of Governours will one time or other be opened to ſee, that theſe Men really ſtrip them of all Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All our Churches</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>are open, (p.</hi> 8.) and every one furniſhed with a bold Swearer; But what's this to the purpoſe? Or how does it anſwer the Caſe I put? For may they not on that account be ſhut at any time, and for a longer time, than they were in the Reign of King <hi>John?</hi> And let me deſire you, Sir, to remember, though you have ſhut us out, That the Church is not tyed to the Walls, but follows the Authority, of which we ſhall Diſcourſe anon. What he means by his Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of 12000. to 16000. and 2000. to 10000. I cannot imagine, unleſs it be to expoſe the Apoſtacy and Iniquity of theſe Times, which none before can parallel: If he mean to upbraid us with the fewneſs of our Number, it is only to encreaſe their own Shame and Reproach; for Argument in this Caſe, it is none, or of no Force; for it might as well have been pleaded againſt the Church in <hi>Elijah</hi>'s time, and he might for the ſame Reaſon have condemned all Chriſtians in general, becauſe Chriſt calls them his <hi>Little Flock.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas I alledged and proved, <hi>That the Oaths were made a condition of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion to us,</hi> quatenùs <hi>Miniſters.</hi> He could not deny this, only it ſeems we muſt be like Pelicans in the Wilderneſs, and none muſt come near us; <hi>For if we will ſeparate we may, but then we muſt ſeparate alone: For the People can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not joyn with us without being guilty of a notorious Schiſm. (p.</hi> 8.) But if Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters fall under a Deprivation, which hath neither Cauſe for the Ground, nor Authority for the Act, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is null and void in it ſelf; May not a Miniſter's own Flock joyn with him without being guilty of notorious Schiſm? And if other Miniſters will not only juſtifie ſuch unjuſt Proceedings, but greedily rob them of their Lively<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods, and enter upon their Charges; May not thoſe, who receive the Wrong, ſeparately do their Duties? But here he objects, <hi>That this is nothing to the People, of whom, as Church Members, this is not required. And this</hi> (he ſays) <hi>is a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Point, and what I durſt not touch upon.</hi> The Point indeed is tender; and though I had not Courage enough to ſwear, <hi>i. e.</hi> to be Perjured, yet my noble Hector ſhall find, that I dare do any thing that is Honeſt. It is not the Oaths in themſelves, nor their taking, or our refuſing, upon which we merely juſtifie the Separation, but it is the influence thoſe Oaths have upon Communion, and that is ſuch as will not only juſtifie, but oblige the People, as well as the Papiſts to ſeparate: And if this be ſo, then it is your ſelves muſt <hi>Separate alone,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the People ought not to joyn with you. For though the Oaths them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are not impoſed on the People as condition of Communion, yet the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57050:6"/>
Matter and Subſtance of thoſe Oaths is put into the Prayers of the Church; and ſo far it becomes a condition of Communion to all Perſons. For to every Prayer the People are required to ſay <hi>Amen;</hi> and they are not left at their Liberty to joyn in what Prayers they will, and not in others, but are required not only to joyn, but to teſtifie their joyning in all; their Amen ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes their joynt conſent, concurrence, and approbation. What People are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned in the ſolemn Worſhip to pray for, is made a condition of Communion to them; and if it be Sinful, will not only juſtifie, but require a Separation: For what I may not ſwear, though but once, I may much leſs pray for daily; nor can there be a greater af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front offered to the Divine Goodneſs, than by ſolemn Prayer to endeavour to engage it for that, which, at the ſame time, I condemn as Unjuſt and Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. How can I joyn with thoſe, in every time of whoſe ſolemn Worſhip, I am required more then once to pray to God, that he would approve and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per the breach of his Commandments, and moſt ſignally and notoriouſly the Fifth, Sixth, and Eighth? To pray not only for that which is highly unjuſt, but alſo for the Proſperity and Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of it, is that which no Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ought to do; and where he is enjoyned to do it, he not only may, but ought to ſeparate from ſuch; and ſo I leave others to judge, whether there be any Reaſon for <hi>the Peoples non Communion,</hi> (as he Styles it.) Other Reaſons I could add, but becauſe the Author of <hi>The Caution againſt Inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency</hi> has clearly proved, That thoſe who think the Oaths unlawful ought, for the ſame Reaſon, to condemn the Prayers, which relate the Matter of the Oath, and conſequently ought not to joyn, where they, by being inſerted in the daily Office, are made a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Communion; I refer to that for more full Satisfaction in that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. Only this I ſhall add, that in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the Church Prayers we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn Thanks to God, <hi>Who hath given us Grace with one accord to make our Prayers and Supplications.</hi> Now let Men pretend what they will, in repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Prayer either they ſay true or falſe; if they ſay true, then they joyn in thoſe Prayers which contain the Matter of the Oath; but if they do not joyn in thoſe Prayers, then this Prayer is a lye in their Mouths.</p>
            <p>Yet there is one thing more I ſhall propound, That though perſonal Failings of any Man are not a good Warrant to others to abſtain from Communion, whether nevertheleſs the Teaching, Preaching, and Maintaining Immorali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Opinions deſtructive of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Practice, may not as well juſtifie a Separation from ſuch, as Errors in the Faith? For though our Adverſaries do not ſay, That Perjury is lawful, yet they argue upon ſuch Principles, as if there could hardly be any ſuch thing: They make Oaths to be no Security to any Governours, which is enough to make all Governours hate and root out that Religion which teacheth ſo. The effect of their Diſcourſe tends to the deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all Faith, Truth, and Juſtice, amongſt Mankind; than which nothing can be more ſcandalous or dangerous to that Religion, which preſcribes and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires the higheſt Simplicity and Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. And this thing alone, I think, may go a great way towards juſtifying a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration from ſuch Perſons.</p>
            <p>From what hath been ſaid, the Anſwer is eaſie to what follows: For it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, That it is not barely a Political Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity required of us; <hi>nor do we</hi> (and God forbid either we or any others ſhould) <hi>Revenge our Wrongs upon the Church,</hi> as he maliciouſly inſinuates: But we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve our own Innocency, and, what in us lyes, by lawful and honeſt Means, the Churches Purity and juſt Authority; though we heartily mourn, That the Wickedneſs of others hath unavoidably
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57050:6"/>
put us upon the neceſſity of taking the Courſe we now do.</p>
            <p>As to that, which he calls my ſecond Argument, he tells me in the Firſt place, That <hi>I proceed upon a groſs Miſtake, by confounding</hi> Deprivation <hi>with</hi> Degrada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and yet, with his leave, the Miſtake was not mine; for I called it Depriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as he doth, I never mentioned Degradation. But if the Civil Power inflict a Penalty under the name of Deprivation, which tantamounts to a Degradation, I could only argue againſt it as it was. Now, to take away a Character, and make it eternally uſeleſs, is in effect the ſame thing; and this is the Caſe; we are not only deprived of our Livelihoods, and ſhut out from our proper Cures, but perpetually diſcharged from the Exerciſe of the Miniſterial Function, unleſs we will ſin againſt the known Laws of God and the Land, and the Dictates of our own Conſciences; which we ought not, upon any account, to do: And I think this wants very little of being equivalent to a Degradation, let them call it by what Name they will. But what if the Civil Power never ſo much as thought of your Diſtinction; as I am apt to think they little Regard it? When the High-Prieſt and Rulers of the Jews firſt conſulted and reſolved amongſt themſelves, <hi>ſtraitly to threaten the Apoſtles, That they ſpeak henceforth to no Man in this</hi> (i. e. <hi>Chriſt's) Name, (Act.</hi> 4 17.) and after put their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves in Execution, expreſly comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them, <hi>not to Speak at all, nor Teach in the Name of</hi> Jeſus, <hi>(verſ.</hi> 18.) do you think they troubled their heads with your Diſtinction of <hi>Deprivation</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gradation?</hi> And how much is our Caſe different? For we are obliged, what in them lyes, either not to ſpeak in that Name, or to act contrary to it; and therefore I think we may very juſtly take up the Apoſtles Anſwer, <hi>Whether it be right in the ſight of God, to hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken unto you, more than unto God, judge ye. (verſ.</hi> 19.) When the Heathen Emperors, who ſet themſelves againſt Chriſtianity it ſelf, Baniſh'd the Biſhops, and Martyr'd others, they did but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive them; they would not for all the World ſure have thought of degrading them. And after all, what if your new Maſters do aſſert that Power in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? You know many of them are <hi>Eraſtians;</hi> and how much ſuch Men ſet by your Diſtinction, you can ſcarce be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. But to go a little farther with you, thoſe Men who pretend to make Laws, are commonly preſumed beſt to underſtand their Meaning. Now it is not long ſince, that a haughty Member of the Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion plainly told me, That it was in their power to take away our Orders, and Unprieſt and Unbiſhop us; for which he gave this worſhipful Reaſon, That the Legiſlative Power ought not to be ſtinted: And thus neither the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority nor Eſtabliſhment of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or his Chriſt, nor the Bounds of Good and Evil, muſt be ſuffered to ſet any Limits to a proud pragmatical Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventioner. By this you may ſee, That the Saviours you adore, reckon, That our being at any time <hi>in Statu quo,</hi> lyes wholly at their Mercy; and that even your ſelves, if you do not abſolutely pleaſe your new Maſters, and go through Stitch, Right or Wrong, with their Commands, can pretend to little Benefit from your Character or Orders. Beſides, I have lately heard of a Man, who hath accepted a Commiſſion to viſit all the Exempts in the City of <hi>London,</hi> and within Ten Miles of it; by Vertue of which, for any thing I know, a buſie Chego-pated Prieſt, may inſolently at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to Viſit his Metropolitan: And whether this may not be improved in time to grant by Commiſſion the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of Epiſcopal Juriſdiction to any Perſons, whom they pleaſe, without Regard to Orders, I cannot ſay, but I think it is a prety Step, and fair Advance towards it.</p>
            <p>But be the Miſtake whoſe it will, I ſhall now try what he anſwers to the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57050:7"/>
Argument; for it is that, which is the Concern: And here he deals moſt diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniouſly by me. For, Firſt, in reciting my Argument, he leaves out thoſe Words, which would have cleared my Meaning; and others, wherein the Strength of my Argument lay. Next, he Sums up my Argument falſly, and not in my Senſe: And after this, he gives no direct Anſwer to it, but raiſeth three Queſtions, and thoſe too for the ſake of ſome Anſwers he had found in Archdeacon <hi>Maſon;</hi> and thoſe Anſwers come not up to the Caſe. Such mighty pains are ſome Men at to ſay nothing to the purpoſe. But however we muſt wait his Motions.</p>
            <p>My Argument he Sums up thus, <hi>That being they (i. e.</hi> the Clergy,) <hi>receive their Authority from God, no Civil Power can diſable them from the Exerciſe of their Duty: And if it doth, they are bound to quit the Communion of the Church, where ſo diſabled.</hi> Now I was ſo far from ſimply aſſerting<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That the Civil Power cannot diſable them from exerciſing their Function, that I there inſtanced in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes where they lawfully might. But as he has worded it, he confutes himſelf. For if they exerciſe only (as he calls it) their Duty, it is certain no Civil Power lawfully can diſable them from the Exerciſe of it. And if he grant it their Duty in that Caſe, he juſtifies them: For no Man ought to be hindred from diſcharging his Duty. Nor did I ſay, That <hi>they are bound to quit the Communion of the Church, where ſo diſabled:</hi> For the Church might own them, when the State diſallowed them. I ſaid, in ſuch Caſe of unjuſt Deprivation, they might exerciſe their Office at their Peril; which either might be done in the Church, or in Separation from that particular Church, according as the Doctrines there taught, and the Terms of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in it ſtood.</p>
            <p>The Argument being thus falſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented, he anſwers it with Queſtions. The method, I ſuppoſe, is new, and he a Man in faſhion. The firſt is this, <hi>Whether a Biſhop duly Conſecrated, or a Miniſter duly Ordained, may not be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Suſpended and Deprived from the Execution of his Office, by the Secular Power, wh<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re there is ſufficient Reaſon for it?</hi> Now this Queſtion plainly anſwers it ſelf. For I think any thing may be done, for which there is <hi>a ſufficient Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon;</hi> and he is a very hard hearted Man, who will not allow him this. But then there are other Queſtions to be asked, <hi>viz.</hi> What is, in ſuch Caſe, a ſufficient Reaſon? Whether there be ſufficient Reaſon in this particular Caſe? And laſtly, (if he pleaſe,) Whether no Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in the Deprivers, and no Crime, as to them, in the Deprived, be a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Reaſon for Suſpenſion or Depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation? It is an odd way of anſwering a Man in a particular Caſe, to float in generals, and keep as far from the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion as may be; but perhaps he will mend that anon; at preſent we muſt attend to the Solution of his Queſtion, which in his Singular way he performs by reciting two Objections, and as many Anſwers to them, from Mr. <hi>Maſon.</hi> And, to make ſhort work, I will grant him all that <hi>Maſon</hi> ſays, where there is, as our Author calls it, <hi>a ſufficient Reaſon for ſo doing;</hi> and I hope he would not have it done without or againſt Reaſon. And ſo, paſſing by the Act of Parliament, which he hath left me to peruſe at lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, till I have more ſpare time, I will directly come to his ſecond Queſtion, and try whether he hath any better For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune there.</p>
            <p>He is not agreed with himſelf, how he ſhall word his ſecond Queſtion; and therefore I will ſet down that, where he expreſſeth himſelf moſt at large, and maintains the afirmative; <hi>Whether it may not be lawful for the Secular Power to deprive Perſons in Orders, for Crimes committed againſt the State, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, upon Refuſal to give Security to the Government for their Peaceable Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour and Allegiance, by Oath?</hi> This
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57050:7"/>
he affirms, and he ſays <hi>I expreſly deny;</hi> which is expreſly falſe, as may appear from thoſe very Words of mine, which he hath cited to prove his Aſſertion: For there I did allow a Deprivation by the Secular Power, where either <hi>the juſt Cenſure of the Church had paſſed on any, or they did merit Depoſition;</hi> and that I think they may do, though a Cenſure be not actually paſſed upon them. But if you will have the Deprivation valid even to their acquieſcence, where the Secular Power, or that which calls it ſelf a Secular Power ſays, that a Crime is committed againſt it, you muſt not only juſtifie Queen <hi>Mary</hi> in Depriving <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth's Biſhops, but you muſt condemn thoſe deprived Biſhops for making a Schiſm, and not joyning in Communion as Laymen, <hi>i. e.</hi> that they did not turn Papiſts.</p>
            <p>But let us examine his Defence. <hi>I anſwer</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>with</hi> Maſon, <hi>Where was the Act of the Church, in the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of</hi> Ablathar? <hi>And where was the Eccleſiaſtical Crime he was charged with?</hi> Did <hi>Maſon</hi> then uſe thus to anſwer with Queſtions? But your Queſtions ſhall have Anſwers however; And, Firſt, I think it not very clear whether the Jewiſh Church did afford ſo ſufficient an Eccleſiaſtical Remedy againſt their Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal High Prieſt, as the Chriſtian Church doth againſt Criminal Biſhops; and if ſo, then it was altogether neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary both for Church and State, that their King, who was of God's own ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, and ſomething more than a mere Secular Perſon, ſhould interpoſe his Authority without any deference to Eccleſiaſtical Cenſure. Secondly, You may enquire, but I am apt to believe that neither you nor I can certainly tell, whether <hi>Abiathar</hi> was Cenſured by the Sanhedrim or not; for if it be not Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded that he was; ſo neither is it that he was not. Thirdly, Though it be very convenient in it ſelf, agreeable to the Rules of the Church, and makes much for the Peace both of Church and State, That Chriſtian Kings in Puniſhing Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticks would take the Cenſures of the Church along with them, which would make the Condemnation of ſuch Perſons more terrible and notorious; yet if the Clergy ſhould refuſe, as it would be their Fault, ſo it doth not hinder the Secular Power to puniſh Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders according to Juſtice. But all this is nothing to the purpoſe, and will do him no ſervice, becauſe there are Caſes, wherein Eccleſiaſticks, Deprived by even a lawful Secular Power, may yet remain obliged to execute their Commiſſion from Chriſt, though at their Peril; or elſe the Apoſtles and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Biſhops muſt be Condemned; and if ſo, it is much more Lawful, when for adhering to right they are deprived only by a pretended Power. But I ſuppoſe this <hi>Virtuoſo</hi> will ſay, That <hi>Jehojada</hi> had been bound to leave of all care of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging his Duty of High Prieſt, if <hi>Athaliah</hi> had Deprived him. As to his Second Queſtion, <hi>(Where was the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Crime</hi> Abiathar <hi>was charged with?)</hi> I anſwer, That though I ſpake of Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures, yet I did never limit the matter to pure Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Crimes, nor have I (that I can remember) ſo much as uſed that Phraſe; for the Church may cenſure whatſoever is <hi>Contra bonos mores,</hi> though, at the ſame time, the Secular Power puniſh it as an Offence againſt the State: The one is Spiritual, and tends to their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and Amendment, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently is for their Good: The other reſpects their Deſerts, and the ill effects it had on the State, and repays and puniſheth their Miſdeeds. But if he would know <hi>Abiathar</hi>'s Crime, it was <hi>High Treaſon,</hi> which is a thing of ſo ſcandalous and dangerous a Nature, that he becomes unfit to diſcharge ſo ſacred an Office, who is guilty of it; nor can the Cenſures of the Church be too ſevere againſt ſuch Wickedneſs; when the Sons of Peace, and thoſe which ſhould teach and pay the ſtricteſt Obedience,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57050:8"/>
though they meet even with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Diſcouragements, ſhall turn Maſters of Miſrule, the Church ought to ſpew them out. As for <hi>Abiathar,</hi> he had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited his Life by his Treaſonable Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, (I do not ſay by joyning with the Son againſt the Father) and in ſuch a caſe he who only reſtrained his Actions, but granted him both Life and an honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Subſiſtance, was very kind. But whether this come neareſt to our Caſe or theirs, I leave ſucceeding Time, and more impartial Poſterity to judge.</p>
            <p>He farther anſwers with the ſame learned Author to this effect, <hi>That a Law was made, That all Magiſtrates, whether Sacerdotal or Civil, ſhould take an Oath that the Queen, (i. e.</hi> Elizabeth) <hi>was Supream.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>under the Pain of Depoſition: For refuſing this, the Popiſh Biſhops were deprived, as preſumed to be for the Pope's Supremacy.</hi> But then he adds, <hi>The ſame Parity of Reaſon may hold for adminiſtring and taking the Oath of Allegiance to,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i. e.</hi> Becauſe Biſhops might be deprived for refuſing an Oath to a lawful Power, againſt an unlawful; therefore they may be deprived for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to take an Oath to an unlawful Power, againſt that which is lawful and rightful. And this he calls Parity of Reaſon, though an indifferent Perſon would ſay it were directly contrary to it; and that the Legality and Rightful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Power, being the Reaſon of the Oath to one, was a juſt Reaſon of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying it the other.</p>
            <p>The ſame Author, he ſays, tells us, That when <hi>thoſe Biſhops</hi> would not take the Oath, <hi>Epiſcopatibus ſuis tandem ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando juxta Legem Parliamentariam ſunt abdicati.</hi> And now he thinks he hath undone me: For he tells me <hi>he leaves me this to Engliſh.</hi> If I cannot, I will come to him for help; though I think I ſhall be very ill employed, if I do. But after all, I believe this Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence was particularly pitched upon for the ſake of ſome Words in it. And firſt, he had an Eye to the Word <hi>abdicati,</hi> as a fine clinch on the Times, and grateful to his new Maſters. What a lucky hit was this, to find ſuch a Word in a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable Clergy-man? Well! let them make their beſt on't: It is not to be doubted, but they will never ſtick at Abdicating Biſhops, who make no Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Abdicating Kings. His next Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect was to the <hi>Legem Parliamentariam,</hi> which ſeemed to be a prety Offering to his Goddeſs <hi>Diana,</hi> the <hi>Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons;</hi> for which they can do no leſs than nominate him to Preach before them the next Seſſions, and then he will forfeit his Conſcience, rather than miſs <hi>the Thanks of the Houſe.</hi> And yet I muſt tell him, That it is an Impropriety of Speech in his Author: For though the Parliament contrive, compoſe, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, yet they are the King's Laws, whoſe <hi>Fiat</hi> it is which makes them ſo. But the ſubtilleſt Fetch of all is in the Word <hi>Epiſcopatibus;</hi> which may ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their Temporalities, and the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of Epiſcopal Juriſdiction in their proper Dioceſſes, as it doth in this place; or elſe may ſignifie the Function and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it ſelf. Now, he durſt not Engliſh it in this latter Senſe, for fear of giving up the whole Order, and being charged with down right <hi>Eraſtianiſm:</hi> And yet he was willing to leave it with an <hi>Inu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndo,</hi> as if it ought to be taken in that ſenſe that ſo he might gratifie the Secular Power with a boundleſs Authority: For thence are his Hopes; and ſome Men care not to betray their whole Order, ſo they can enrich themſelves. Thus, Sir, I have Engliſhed your Latin by Piecemeal, and, to requite your Favour, I leave it to you to put together again.</p>
            <p>His Third Queſtion is this, <hi>Whether if a Perſon be lawfully Deprived of the Exerciſe of his Miniſtry, he is notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding bound, as a private Member, to communicate in that Church? &amp;c.</hi> This he ſays, I deny, which is a falſe and impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Slander; for nothing can be more plain, than that he, who is lawfully De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived ought to acquieſce; the only
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57050:8"/>
Remedy left him in that caſe, is by all lawful means to get it off again as ſoon as he can. But he knows we deny the lawfulneſs of the Deprivation, upon which account we think it lawful for us to continue the Exerciſe of our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, and would do it in conjunction with them, were it not that they both unjuſtly approve our pretended Depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and refuſe to ſuffer us the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of our Miniſtry, either in our own or their Churches, and alſo further clog their Communion with ſuch Terms, as is not lawful for us to comply with; and upon this ſcore we think we both may, and ought to maintain <hi>a ſeparate Communion.</hi> You ſhould have proved the Deprivation lawful, which you knew we denied; but inſtead of that, you all a long run away begging the Queſtion.</p>
            <p>This ſhould have been the Laſt, but being a fruitful She Queſtion, it hath foaled Two more, and how many it may bring forth in time, Who knows? Like Twins he has put them together, and ſo let them go. <hi>Whether Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion oblige ſuch a one to the actual Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of his Office, when forbid by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate? And then, Whether for the Exerciſe of his Miniſtry, he may and is obliged to ſet up and maintain a ſeparate Communion?</hi> And that I may comply with his way as far as I can, I will anſwer them with two more. Firſt, Whether the Apoſtles, having received their Commiſſion and Authority from Chriſt, were obliged to leave off the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Exerciſe of their Office, when forbid by the Magiſtrate? Secondly, Whether if a Separation be made, thoſe who depart from others, or thoſe who give juſt Cauſe for it are the Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks? But theſe I muſt leave to him, that we may examine how he ſolves his own. <hi>If</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Magiſtrate may lawfully Deprive, then the Clerk may be lawfully Deprived, and if ſo, he is bound to ſubmit.</hi> Still this is begging the Queſtion; for we complain not of what is lawfully, but what is unlawfully done. But he gives a Reaſon, which either proves too much, or manifeſtly ſhews, That he thinks either that the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates Deprivation is always lawful, or though it ſhould be unlawful, yet muſt be ſubmitted to. <hi>For</hi> (ſaith, he <hi>p.</hi> 13, 14.) <hi>to officiate notwithſtanding ſuch a Prohibition, is in our way to take up Arms<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> againſt him; and in a lower, to do what the Pope doth in a higher Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to controul his Juriſdiction.</hi> Now this is a Knaviſh malicious Trick, to compare our Actions to the Popes; the Pope directly challengeth a Supremacy over Kings, indeed over all Men; we only lay claim to a Chriſtian Liberty, not to comply with Sin and Wickedneſs, though the Magiſtrate command it; and a Power not to deſert our Station, wherein Chriſt hath fixed us, for every humourſom or unjuſt Prohibition of the State, but at our Peril, and without Reſiſtance; and what Agreement hath this with the Popes Actions? But if his Civil Magiſtrate may not any ways be controuled, but muſt be complied with in all things, then I leave any indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Perſons to judge, whether theſe two things be not the direct Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of his Arguments. Firſt, This makes the Proceedings of the Apoſtles, and all the Primitive Chriſtians, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagating the Goſpel for about Three hundered Years, to be altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtifyable. For they were actually prohibited firſt by the Jews, after by the Emperours; ſo that if his Doctrine had taken place, Chriſtianity had never entered into the World. Secondly, This ſhuts out the Doctrine of the Croſs, not only as Fooliſhneſs, but as Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Diſobedience, and puts it in the Power of the Civil Magiſtrate at his Pleaſure to extirpate Chriſtianity out of the World; for if prohibited, they muſt ceaſe and comply; becauſe to do otherwiſe <hi>Were in their way to take up Arms againſt him, and controul his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction.</hi> And thus, if the Grand
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:57050:9"/>
Signior ſhould Silence all the <hi>Chriſtian Miniſters</hi> in his Dominions, they muſt hold their Peace, and no more ſpeak in the Name of Jeſus; for if they do our Author will tell them, they are Rebels. I perceive this Author makes uſe of his Religion only for his Conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience, and will put no more on than he can at any time put off again; he is here a ſort of a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and at <hi>Japan</hi> would be a <hi>Hollander.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to make good his Argument, he accuſeth me of Ignorance as to the Primitive Times, and inſtanceth in <hi>Euſtathius</hi> of <hi>Antioch, Athanaſius</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and <hi>Paulus</hi> of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> put out by the Imperial Power; and this he ſays, <hi>Was never queſtioned by the Orthodox, though they complained of the Injuſtice of it,</hi> &amp;c. Now I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that I have not had thoſe Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages which ſome have been happy in; and am content to be accounted Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, provided he will ſuffer me to be Honeſt: But, yet as Ignorant as I am, I think, no Man that had conſulted his Cauſe, or his own Reputation would have produced this inſtance in this caſe. For it will either juſtifie our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, or force him to condemn theſe Perſons; and in ſo good Company we ſhall the leſs value hard Cenſures: For were they thruſt out of their Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes? What great difference is here? Are not our Livelihoods and Cures taken from us? Are not our Biſhops Deprived of their Profits and the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of their Juriſdictions? This we ſuffer, and do not ſo much as compare the Power then and now, whether law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful or unlawful: If the Civil Authority wrongfully ſpoil us of our Goods, and reſtrain our Perſons, we know no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance any more then thoſe good Men did. But did they forbear to exerciſe their Office and Miniſtry where they had opp<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tunity? No ſuch thing. Was there no Schiſm upon this account? It is plain, That the Orthodox refuſed to Communicate with the Biſhops put over them; the whole Chriſtian World was concerned on one ſide or other in the Caſe of <hi>Athanaſius;</hi> at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> the People were ſo troubleſome, that the Emperor was forced to recal <hi>Paulus,</hi> though he was after again Baniſhed; and upon the Expulſion of <hi>Euſtathius</hi> from <hi>Antioch,</hi> the ſuſpected Biſhops, ſet over them, were diſguſted by many, and <hi>Theodoret</hi> ſays, That <hi>plurimi Studioſi pietatis, cùm Sacerdotes tùm Plebs, deſertis Eccleſiaſticis caetibus, privatim Convenie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant</hi> (lib. 1. cap. 21.) And this they continued to do, though all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches were taken away from the Adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents to <hi>Euſtathius,</hi> in order to force them to Communion with thoſe put in his place, as may appear from that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of <hi>Athanaſius</hi> to the Emperor, for one Church to be granted to the Orthodox at <hi>Antioch,</hi> when he deſired the like of <hi>Athanaſius</hi> for the Arrians at <hi>Alexandria (Theod. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 12.) I think a Man ſo Skilful in Antiquity might have made choiſe of ſome more lucky inſtance; but that he may not be at too much trouble, if he can have a little Patience, it ſhall not be long ere I furniſh him.</p>
            <p>Next in order to an Anſwer to his. Second Queſtion, he ſuppoſeth the Clergy-man not bound by the Depriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but then (ſaith he) <hi>What is this to a Separation? For is he ſo obliged, that rather then not officiate, he may and ought to break of from Communion with the Church?</hi> If you will make that ſuppoſal (which in our particular Caſe is a great Truth) you of all Men were moſt unfit to put theſe Queſtions. For when you joyn with thoſe, who make this unjuſt Deprivation, when you take our Churches, our Flocks, our Lively<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods, and ſuffer us not to exerciſe our Miniſtry, where you have the Profit of it, unleſs we will do it to the diſſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of our Conſciences, Do you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain that we do not maintain Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with you? If we were in fault in this Caſe, yet Modeſty (if any
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:57050:9"/>
be left you) and the ill Uſage we have from your Party, might make you hold your Peace. I freely grant, <hi>That we ought to continue in the Communion of the Church we are of as long as we can, and that Separation is like a Divorce, which is the laſt Extremity,</hi> &amp;c. But then I ſay, That we ſtill are of the ſame Church we were of; for the Schiſm goes along with the Cauſe; and there it is you, not we, are the Schiſmaticks; the Separation I grant to be Unhappy and Miſchievous, but let them look to that who made the Divorce by juſtifying unlawful Proceedings, and ſetting up ſinful Terms of Communion, as I have already proved; and therefore will ſay no more of it here. And this is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for an Anſwer to that Slander, as if we proceeded upon the ſame Grounds with the Diſſenters, which is manifeſtly falſe; only I am bold to tell him, That they have now put a Plea into the Mouth of the Diſſenters, which will juſtifie their Separation from them; and were it not, that they cannot juſtifie their Separation from us, your Perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and other ill Acts had given up the Cauſe to them.</p>
            <p>When he thought he had loſt my Second Argument with multitudes of Queſtions, he attacks that which he calls the Third. And, he ſays, <hi>I argue from the Subjection the People and Clergy owe to the Biſhops, and the Biſhops owe to their Metropolitan;</hi> and I grant, That I do ſo, and the Argument muſt be good, unleſs he can Diſpute away all the Government and Orders of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church. But to this he returns with all imaginable Scorn. <hi>Our Author that undertakes to give us an account of the Senſe, Judgment, and Practice of the Primitive Times, would have done well to have given us a touch or two of his Skill that way, by ſome credeble Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities; and particularly of ſuch a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of the Biſhop to the Metropolitan, to the Confutation of ſome of St.</hi> Cyprian<hi>'s Epiſtles.</hi> It being very likely, that in a ſmall time the whole Controverſie may turn upon this hinge, and it being moſt becoming Church Men to direct Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Proceedings by Eccleſiaſtical Authority, I ſhall take a little more pains in this place to anſwer, not only what he now objects, but to take in what he hath at any time diſperſedly ſpoken as to this Matter. If this ſcornful Gentleman will ſo give up all to the Civil Power, that their Commands, and Orders muſt be actually obeyed and complyed with in every thing, he in effect grants two things (which done by any Clergy-man, to have his Gown pulled over his Ears were too mean a Puniſhment.) Firſt, That it is in their Power to deſtroy Chriſtianity, and in the room of it to plant any other, or none at all. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, That Religion is only an Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice or Sham to be made uſe of, ſo far as it is ſerviceable to the Civil Power, and no otherwiſe. By this you may perceive, what a Friend the Eraſtian is to the Atheiſt; and though our Author doth not ſpeak out, yet he hath many Expreſſions that look earneſtly that way. But he will allow, That the bleſſed Jeſus, who inſtituted the Chriſtian Church, did by a publiſhed Goſpel and Succeſſion of authorized Paſtors pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for the Directing, Ordering, and Governing of that Church, which they are to ſtand by in all Ages and Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; then he muſt grant, That there are ſome Duties of a Chriſtian, which no Civil Power can ſupercede; and though we are not allowed to reſiſt the lawful Civil Power, how hardly ſo ever it uſe us, yet we muſt practice our Duty at our peril; and if the Civil Power would obſtruct it, we muſt then take up our Croſs and follow Chriſt. And if this be not our Caſe, we are miſtaken Sufferers; but if it be, it will very much call in queſtion their Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity.</p>
            <p>To fear God, and honour the King, and not meddle with thoſe, who are given to change, I think, was not
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57050:10"/>
only laid down as a wiſe Man's Advice, but deſigned as a Duty and Obligation upon every particular Perſon. But not to urge here matters of Juſtice, Fidelity, and common Honeſty, (which yet by the way, I think, are never to be ſligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) we are here to conſider what Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations we may lie under with reſpect to the Government, and Orders in the Church. And if he will allow me to reaſon either from the Practice of the Church, or the Canons of the Church, or the Writings of thoſe who beſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood both, particularly St. <hi>Cyprians,</hi> whom he himſelf Magnifies, and than whom no Man better underſtood this Cauſe; then I doubt not but we may go a conſiderable way in it.</p>
            <p>That Epiſcopacy is the higheſt Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in the <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi> and that there is nothing, which one Biſhop as a Biſhop may do, but another may do the ſame, I readily grant; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, That there can be no ſuch thing as <hi>Epiſcopus Epiſcoporum:</hi> But then that there are withal certain Rights, Priviledges, and Prerogatives belonging to the Metropolitan, which have been always thought to have been inſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly annexed to him, and from the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of which other Biſhops have been ever ordinarily debarr'd; and that upon this account, that the Peace and Unity of the Church cannot be otherwiſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, nor the Government managed; this (I ſay) I think to be as plain as the High way.</p>
            <p>Whatever the Rights or Priviledges of Metropolitans may be, I ſhall only Diſcourſe of ſome, which were univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally allowed by the Ancient <hi>Church,</hi> and confirmed by Canons, or Practice uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally received, and which may at leaſt, in ſome meaſure, affect our Caſe; of which one is this, That no one was to be Ordained a Biſhop without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence or conſent of the Metropolitan. <hi>In the 19th. Canon of the 1ſt. Councel of</hi> Antioch, it is thus determined, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>That a Biſhop ſhall not be Ordained with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Synod and the Preſence of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitan.</hi> And when in the ſame Canon they had made the actual Preſence of the Metropolitan, as neceſſary as ſuch a caſe could permit, they add, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>That if any thing be done other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then as was than determined, the Ordination ſhall be invalid.</hi> Now this very Canon was only purſuant to a Canon of the Councel of <hi>Nice;</hi> and becauſe moſt Men, eſpecially thoſe with whom we have now to do, have, at leaſt formerly, pretended a great Veneration for that Ancient Councel, we will ſee what was their Judgment, which in the 6th. Can. you may find expreſſed thus.—<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Let this be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally known, that if any one be Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained a Biſhop without the conſent of the Metropolitan, This great Counſel doth determine, that ſuch a one ought to be no Biſhop.</hi> Perhaps it was for this Reaſon, That <hi>Euſebius</hi> (as far as I remember) in reckoning up the Eccleſiaſtical Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, except <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> (for which there might be particular Reaſons) mentions only Metropolitical Sees. For whilſt the Rights of the Metropolitan were preſerved, and his Succeſſion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted, it was ſcarce poſſible, that the other Biſhops of the Province ſhould come in any other way, but at the right Door; for he was either to be actually at, or conſent their to Ordination by Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops ſummoned by him for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; ſo that as the being ſure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning him, removed away all doubt of the reſt; ſo the being uncertain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning him, of courſe makes all the Ordinations in his time uncertain. This I ſay, that you may conſider what will be the effect of Setting up a Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litan againſt a Metropolitan, and how it is a fair way to render the validity
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:57050:10"/>
of the Miniſterial Function called in queſtion. But of what force ſuch an Act would be, if done, I ſhall conſider preſently.</p>
            <p>Another matter appropriated by the univerſal Church to the Metropolitan, was, that nothing of Moment, which might concern the Province, or be of general Concernment, ſhould be done without his privity and conſent; ſo that unjuſtly to ſet a Metropolitan aſide, and for other Biſhops to neglect him, is to make matters of greateſt Moment, and neareſt Concernment to the Church to become impracticable; and to draw a Scandal upon the Actions of all Biſhops, as to any thing they ſhall do in ſuch Caſes; and when I have offered Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities for the Proof of this, I leave others to judge whether they are <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible</hi> enough for ſuch a Huff as our Author. Amongſt thoſe Ancient Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, collected and received before the Councel of <hi>Nice,</hi> which are vulgarly called the Apoſtles Canons, the 34th. runs thus, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. i. e. <hi>The Biſhops of every Country ought to obſerve him, who is their Firſt (or Chief) and to eſteem him as their Head, and to do nothing of Moment without his Conſent. Every other Biſhop to employ himſelf only about thoſe things, which are buſineſs of his proper Dioceſ<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and the Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages (or Places) thereunto belonging. Neither let him</hi> (i. e. <hi>the Chief) do any thing without the Concurrence of the reſt. And ſo <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity ſhall be preſerved, and God ſhall be gloryfied,</hi> &amp;c. To this very Canon the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> relates, and explains what is meant by the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the firſt amongſt them.</hi> For after a great deal of care taken about the Ordination of the Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litan, as a Matter of great moment for the Churches Security, they conclude the Canon thus, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>(Can.</hi> 4.) i. e. <hi>Let the Authority</hi> (or Confirmation) of things done <hi>throughout every Province belong to the Metropolitan.</hi> Upon this very Canon did the <hi>African</hi> Fathers found their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for that ſaying in their Epiſtle to <hi>Coeleſtine,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome, Decreta Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coena, ſiv<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> inferioris gradûs Clericus, ſive ipſos Epiſcopos, ſuis Metropolitanis aper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſime commiſerunt.</hi> i. e. <hi>The Decrees of the Council of</hi> Nice <hi>have moſt plainly put, not only the Clergy of inferiour Rank, but even the Biſhops themſelves, under the Juriſdiction of their Metropolitans.</hi> And to both the foregoing Canons the Council of <hi>Antioch</hi> ſeems plainly to referr, in their 9th <hi>Can.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> i. e. <hi>It behoves the Biſhops in every Province, to know the Biſhop of the Metropolitical See, and that he undertakes the Care and Management of the whole Province; and that by reaſon of the great Concourſe of People from all places to the Metropolis, upon account of Buſineſs,</hi> &amp;c. And having thus confirmed the Juriſdiction of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitans, they tell you, That they did it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. i. e. <hi>According to an ancient Canon of our Fathers, binding,</hi> (or in force.) And that you may know what particular Canon in this they had an eye to, in the very next Words, ſpeaking of the Duty of Biſhops, they expreſſed it thus, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; which are the very words uſed in the Apoſtles Canon for the ſame purpoſe, as any one may ſee, who will compare them together. From all this it is evident, That even Biſhops
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:57050:11"/>
place at <hi>Rome,</hi> it made a Schiſm, and it had been a very Pernicious one, had not <hi>Felix</hi> opportunely died. I will not urge upon our Author, That his frequent looſe way of expreſſing himſelf doth, in effect, baſely give up, not only the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Order, but all the Orders in Chriſt's Church, and conſequently the Church it ſelf, to the Secular Power, be it what it will; if this was done deſignedly, (as it ſeems to be) it is ſo much the worſe: But I will keep my ſelf to regular Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Practices and Authorities; and if a Clergy-man will not abide by theſe, or return them a fair Anſwer, he is much more fit for a Cenſure than a Diſputation.</p>
            <p>It is a Rule ſo well known to be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally received by the Ancient Church, <hi>That there ſhall be but one Biſhop in a City,</hi> that I need not ſpend time to prove it. That of the <hi>Chorepiſcopi</hi> doth not alter the caſe, and particularly is nothing to our caſe, for theſe two Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Firſt, That though they were a ſort of Rural Biſhops, yet they were only as Aſſiſtants, and acted in Subordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to, and by the Direction of the City Biſhop. Secondly, That we have none ſuch now; and as for thoſe, who are ſo haſty to get into the places of our pretendly deprived Biſhops, they would never own themſelves to be <hi>Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repiſcopi,</hi> but challenge the whole entire Juriſdiction, and abſolutely thruſt out the lawful Canonical Biſhops, contrary to all the Rules of the Church. The reaſon why this Rule bath been held ſo Sacred, is partly, becauſe to do otherwiſe would be to make the Church a Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; for in St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s Senſe a Church is a People united to their Biſhop; where by the way obſerve, That the Word <hi>Plebs,</hi> or People, is taken in a larger Senſe, as well for the Clergy as Layety under the Juriſdiction of one Biſhop: And here the Biſhop ſupplying the place of the Head, and the People of the Body; to ſet up two Biſhops were to make two Heads; partly becauſe if two Powers, independent upon each other, command and direct in the ſame Church, it would breed ſuch Diſorders and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions as uſually end in Schiſm; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it might make the Obedience of the People impoſſible, whilſt they might command different things at the ſame time; and for this reaſon both ſo great Power was given to Metropolitans in Provincial Churches, and all Biſhops were Prohibited any Acts of Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on out of their own Precincts, which might be any ways prejudicial to the Canonical Biſhop of the Place. And therefore where there is a lawful Biſhop, another ought not to be placed there; if it be otherwiſe, the whole Act is void; and this, Sir, your good Friend St. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> will tell you, <hi>Epiſcopo ſemel Facto, &amp; Collegarum ac Plebis teſtimonio &amp; ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicio comprobato, alium conſtitui nullo modo poſſe.</hi> (Ep. 41. ad Cornel.) This, I think, is plain enough; but becauſe our Author is for abundance of Words, if he pleaſe to read St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s Epiſtle to <hi>Antoſvianus,</hi> who favoured <hi>Novatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> in ſuch a caſe as is daily expected will be ours, he may there find Reaſons, as well as bare Aſſertions, of which take this taſte; <hi>Cum nemo ante ſe</hi> (he ſpeaks of <hi>Cornelius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome) factus eſſet, cùm Fabiani locus,</hi> i. e. <hi>cum loous Petri &amp; gradus Cathedr<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Sacerdotalis vacaret, quo occupato de dei voluntate, atque omnium noſtrúm conſeaſione firmato; quiſquis jam Epiſcopus fieri voluit, foris fiat neceſſe eſt, nec habeat Eccleſiaſticam Ordinationem, qui Eccleſiae non tenct <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitatem; quiſquis ille fuerit, multum de ſe jactans, &amp; ſibi plurimum vindicans, profanus eſt, al<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nus eſt, foris eſt. Et cùm poſt primum ſecundus eſſe non poſſit, quiſquis poſt unum, qui ſolus eſſe debeat, factus eſt, non jam ſecundus ille, ſed nullus eſt.</hi> (Ep. 52.) Thus it is plain, That the grand Reaſon why St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> gives the Cauſe againſt <hi>Novatian,</hi> was, becauſe <hi>Cornelius</hi> in the Vacancy of the See was Can<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>nically placed there before him. If therefore a Biſhop be thruſt into
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:57050:11"/>
the place of another, who is lawfully Biſhop of the Place, all ſuch tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are void and null in themſelves; and all that forſake their true Biſhop, and joyn with him who is thruſt in, are Schiſmaticks; and though there ſhould be any Penalty or Deprivation befall the Biſhop; yet if it be ſuch, which in its own Nature doth only amount to a Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion, it cannot make the Place capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of another Biſhop; becauſe, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the preſent reſtraint, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains Biſhop ſtill, though under a kind of an arreſt; and in ſuch Caſe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of the uſe and exerciſe of that Authority, which all this while is really lodg'd in him, is to be waited and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured.</p>
            <p>From hence, I think, it doth appear, that it was a ruled Caſe in the Church, That if any Perſon did come into any other than a vacant See, and claim there as direct and proper Biſhop, (as <hi>Nova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tianus</hi> did againſt <hi>Cornelius,)</hi> both he and all his adherents were adjudged Schiſmaticks. As to a Vacancy I am ſtill of the ſame Mind, and if our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor would have me change it, he would ſooner have prevailed with me by Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments than Threatnings; I have ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly thought on it, and cannot yet imagine how a Vacancy can be, but one of theſe three ways; either God muſt make the See void by his Death, or a lawful Authority makes it voyd by a lawful Depoſition, or he himſelf makes it void by his Renunciation. For the laſt of theſe, I perceive, our Author has a preſent kindneſs, but how long it may hold I know not. For when others have taken away their Eſtates, he in a pretty ſly way perſwades them to mend the Matter, by renouncing their Order, and, I believe, with much the ſame deſign, that the Fox praiſed the Cock for an excellent Singer, that while he ſhut his Eyes as he crow'd, Reynard might have the opportunity to run in upon him, and make a prey of him; as to the ſecond way, which is Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, I do not ſee that there is the leaſt room for any Plea for it in this Caſe. For be the Authority of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Power what it will, as to the taking away their Eſtates, the conſinement or puniſhment of their Perſons, or the temporary reſtraint of the exerciſe of their Authority; yet, that the Secular Power can unmake a Biſhop, (which is the only thing can, as to them, come up to our Caſe,) I ſtill peremptorily deny: And let our Author clap his Hands and cry S'too, let him ſet all he can on my Back, all the threatnings in the World, nay all the things that can be threatned ſhall never fright me from it; indeed if he can fairly convince me by Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I will yield, and give up my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, when they pleaſe to demand it: But he had beſt have a care what he does; for, in the end, he himſelf would be no Gainer by the Bargain. In the next place, if he fly to an Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Depoſition, there ſeveral things muſt be enquired into. As, Firſt, A ſufficient Cauſe, without which the Act would be manifeſt Injuſtice, if not void. To en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire after all the Cauſes, for which a Biſhop may lawfully be Depoſed, would be too tedious; <hi>Photius</hi> in the 14th. Ch. of his <hi>Nomocanon</hi> refers us to very many, I will not ſay all; our Author may ſearch them at his leaſure, and ſee if he can pick up a new Charge; as for the preſent Accuſation it is a thing of that Nature, that the contrary may rather juſtifie the doing the ſame by others. In the next place there muſt be competent Judges; and the 12th. Canon of the Council of <hi>Carthage</hi> will not allow leſs than Twelve Biſhops to depoſe a Biſhop. But lay all Circumſtances together as our preſent Caſe is, and I am apt to think that there will not be found any compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Authority to ſit in Judgment upon our Biſhops. But he that as it will, When hath any ſuch Authority made any offer that way? Laſtly, There muſt be a full and fair Hearing. And in the cloſe of the 97th. Canon of the Council
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:57050:12"/>
of <hi>Carthage</hi> you may ſee what Horrour the Biſhops expreſſed in the Caſe of <hi>Quedvultdeus</hi> of Depoſing a Biſhop, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Cauſe had a full and final Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Indeed in ſome Caſes the Canons cenſure <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> and then ſuch ſolemn Proceedings are not neceſſary; but even then there muſt be a notoriety of the Fact the Canon relates to, and there muſt be a Declaration, that the Canon takes Place. But I do not ſee that any of theſe things can be ſo much as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in this Caſe, and therefore depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed they are not: The laſt way of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cancy is Death; but of that I need not Diſcourſe, there are (thanks be to God) if not a great, yet a venerable Number of them living; and, I hope, God will long continue their Lives for his Honour, their own Renown, and the Good of this diſtreſſed Church.</p>
            <p>From the foregoing Diſcourſe, theſe Conſequences may be fairly drawn; Firſt, That whoſoever ſhall be put into the Place of the pretended Deprived Biſhops, are not to be eſteemed Biſhops, nor ought either Clergy or People to regard them, but to adhere firmly to their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer true Biſhops. Secondly, That who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall Ordain ſuch, or endeavour to Place them there, make themſelves Criminals, and liable to an Eccleſiaſtical Cenſure. Thirdly, That they and all their adherents are Schiſmaticks. I am accuſtomed to ſpeak my Mind plainly; if this do not pleaſe you, I cannot help it; you were pleaſed to call for Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, I have given you ſome, and when you are at leaſure, I hope I ſhall hear of your Epiſtles.</p>
            <p>Having thus diſpatched the Argument, I think, I need not put in any Anſwer to his impertinent Queſtions; but whereas he ſays, <hi>My Argument will ſerve either way,</hi> as well for the Biſhops and Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politans that have, as thoſe that have not taken the Oaths, he is much miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; for if my Allegation be good, they will be liable to cenſure; and if he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, he will yield that that alters the Caſe. And by this he may perceive, That whatever matters of State have occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, yet it is not bare matters of State we proceed upon, nor do we think it unlawful to ſwear Allegiance to the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Power; and therefore both his Queſtions in that reſpect are Imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent. But I deſire to know what Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians ever thought it lawful to take an Oath of Allegiance, to that which is no Sovereign, againſt that which really is, or to take a later Oath directly contrary to a former lawful Oath? But if he can find none ſuch, if he pleaſe, I can furniſh him with a ſort of Chriſtians in the Primitive Times, who made ſo little Conſcience of Oaths, that <hi>Jura, Perjura; Sacretum proder<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> noli,</hi> is ſaid to be a received Axiome amongſt them; and if theſe are for his turn, I do not envy him their Company. But one great Artifice of our Author, is to take the out skirts, or ſome little ſnips of the Cauſe, and then put Queſtions as if we were concerned about nothing elſe, which is pitiful Sophiſtry; if he pleaſe to deal fairly, and take the whole Caſe together, he may take the liberty to ask as many Queſtions as he pleaſe, and I doubt not but he may be furniſhed with Anſwers. In the mean time I ſhall leave this matter here; and as for what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, it coming not up ſo fairly to the Merits of the Cauſe, I ſhall be very ſhort.</p>
            <p>The next thing that comes upon the Stage, is, <hi>Publick Good,</hi> which, like the <hi>Phoenix,</hi> is born to deſtroy it ſelf; for it is rarely uſed, but when all other Reaſons fail; and commonly then moſt ſtrongly pretended, when the Intention and Deſign is to deſtroy it. Much Fairer and Honeſter it would be, if Men would plead the Juſtice and Righteouſneſs of their Cauſe, and not thus juſtifie the moſt ſhameleſs Treachery and prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Villany under the Diſguiſes and falſe Pretences of Publick Good; but I muſt follow our Author, and it ſhall be as cloſe as I can, that I may the ſooner
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:57050:12"/>
have done with him, and get into better Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. I did ſay, that the task his Author un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook would better become a <hi>Committee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man or Sequeſtrator than a Divine of the Church of</hi> England; and he grants that this had been true, provided it had been true that he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took what I charge him with, <hi>That the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good will Warrant us to deſtroy a lawful King.</hi> As to which I ſhall only ask this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, Whether K. <hi>J.</hi> was our lawful K. or not? If he was, I think they have deſtroyed him as far as they can; that it is not done more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually, is not for want of good Will, but of Power: And if I be not ſtrangely miſtaken, this is the thing which is defended, or which at leaſt ought to be defended; for otherwiſe all the reſt fails. Next he taxeth me, as having <hi>either a bad Memory, or a very bad Conſcience,</hi> for ſaying, That his Author had not proved the matter in <hi>Hypotheſi,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in our particular Caſe;</hi> now a bad Memory is no good thing, but a very bad Conſcience is a very ill thing; but, I think, I have no great cauſe to accuſe either in this Matter. For let them pretend what they will, particular Perſons and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the thing as it really is, they will never be brought to; but here they always ſuppoſe Caſes, which they would have People to belive is ours, or like ours, but never come home to the point. If they would give me leave, I would propound ſome Caſes of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and name Perſons and Actions; ſo that a direct Anſwer muſt unavoidably be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, or the trifling appear; but I would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe theſe Men not to talk too much of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, leaſt they ſhould awaken her, and ſhe ſhould ſing a Song in their Ears, and make their Hearts ake. But before he can come to the Matter, this learned Author in Romances, not being able to find out any thing more contemptible, compares me to Don <hi>Quixot;</hi> but he ſhould have remembred, that he was a kind of a deſperate Fellow, and there may be ſome hazard in undertaking ſuch an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary; however, I believe, I ſhall never miſtake him for an Enchanted Caſtle, or a Wind-mill, though, for any thing I know, he may have one in his Head.</p>
            <p>Three Heads he propounds from my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, of which the laſt is the Notion of Publick Good, and after his Landable Crab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſhion, of going backward, he will needs begin with that; but at laſt I find we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, That Publick Good is good for Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body, but who that Somebody is, it ſeems we are not yet agreed; for, he ſays, it is not a <hi>Perſonal Good,</hi> and yet if it be not good for <hi>Perſons,</hi> I am afraid it will prove good for no Body. If he had pleaſed, he might have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, That I called the Publick Good a <hi>Perſonal Good,</hi> not with reference to Mens pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate ſeparate Intereſt in detriment of the reſt, but with reſpect to them as Perſons in So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety; and doubtleſs Publick Good is in its higheſt Exaltation, when it's Diffuſive to all; but yet in ſome Caſes particular Perſons, or Parties may, and muſt ſuffer for the Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Community, and this I fairly owned, and if he would not ſee it, I cannot help it; but to argue as if I diſowned any ſuch thing, is very Diſingenuous. But if there may be ſome Caſes, wherein it may be the Glory of ſome to ſuffer; Yet will this prove it to be the Publick Good, for ſome Men to raiſe their Fortunes upon the Ruins of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try? I think he might as well ſay, That a Man ought to ſet his Houſe on ſire on purpoſe, that three or four Thieves might have the opportunity to run away with the beſt of his Goods. I know not better how to compare the Publick Good of a Community, than to the ſafety of a human body, when every Part and Member is right, ſound, and well diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and out of danger, it is certainly then beſt with it; but if a blow be made at me, I ſhall rather take it on my Arm than on my Head, though it was intended at my Head, and not at my Arm; and yet, I think, herein the Arm had no injuſtice from the Head or Body, though it had from the external Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, becauſe the uſe of it in ſuch caſe is to defend the Head, and it would have ſuffered more, if the blow had been taken there; and as to internal Diſtempers, ſome are removed by Cure, and every part preſerved; but in caſe the whole be indangered by the diſaffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of a part, then we come to Amputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſpare not a Leg or Arm, or any Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, whereby the Body may be preſerved ſound, though not entire; but then this is a remedy which brings an irrecoverable loſs, leaves a Maim for ever, and is never to be uſed but in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:57050:13"/>
caſes of abſolute Neceſſity; but then if the Diſtemper affect the Head or Heart, as all lawful Means ought to be uſed, ſo all Hazards muſt be run: For nothing can Warrant the cutting off the Head, or pulling out the Heart. Here the whole unavoidably muſt follow the fate of the part, and ſo the Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is worſe than the Diſeaſe, and therefore under no pretence whatſoever to be practiſed. If it be objected, That the Head hath not the ſame Connexion with the Civil and with the Natural Body, and that the Civil Body may be preſerved by a new Head, though not the Natural; I Anſwer, Firſt, That it is the ſafeſt Courſe for the Preſervation of the Society to pay the ſame deference to the Civil Head as to the Natural; and this, I think, our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions do, by making the legal Succeſſion of Kings to be the ſame Head, according to that known Axiome <hi>Rex non moritur.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, That in any Body whatſoever it is moſt unnatural for the Body to conſpire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, and deſtroy the Head. Thirdly, That in this reſpect the Civil Head hath a cloſer Connexion with the Body, than the Natural; that the Ligaments between it and the Body are the Conſtitutions, ſo that let him be dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven where he will, whilſt he is alive and in Being, he will bear the Relation of the Head to the Body, while thoſe Conſtitutions laſt. To alter theſe at pleſure, and Mens Rights with them, is the higheſt Injuſtice; and the ſetting any other Head on than the Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons bear, moſt certainly puts the Body into ſtrange Convulſions, and often ere long brings Ruin upon it. Beware a Common-wealth, my Maſters! Methinks I hear the Magpyes, Daws, Crows and Rooks about the Town, begin to ſet their Notes that way.</p>
            <p>But after all, let all, that can, be allowed to Publick Good; yet it ought to be conſidered whether it be the particular Caſe, and whether the Publick Good be Secured or Advanced. And here it would be enquired, Whether Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion be better Secured to us? Whether Mens Lives and Properties are more Safe? How we encreaſe in Strength, in Trade, in Riches, and the like? And though I do not admire our Gain, yet many of theſe Things are out of my way; but there is a certain Tract, called the <hi>DEAR BARGAIN,</hi> which ſpeaks of theſe Things; and if the Government would encourage that Author to write, I am perſwaded he would quickly ſet that Controverſie in the true Light; and to him as the fitteſt Man I leave it.</p>
            <p>The next thing is the Practicability of this Principle of Publick Good. Now whatever the Publick Good is, or whatever it may War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, yet if People are to make that their Rule, they will judge of it, and then every one will judge of Publick Good according to his own Intereſt and Perſuaſion; and this by ſeveral Arguments I did prove would fill the World with Violence and Confuſion. But he is ſo far from anſwering any of my Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that he never mentioneth one of 'em as ſenſible that it would ſpoil all that he intended to ſham on me afterwards. But very honeſtly he Sums up my Argument, as I neither laid nor meant it, and tells me, That the <hi>Publick Good's being liable to be abuſed,</hi> is an inconcluding Argument, not only becauſe of the Inconſequence, but becauſe <hi>this is a way of Arguing, that may ſerve againſt any thing; and if we put Publick Juſtice, or Laws, or Religion, or Reformation, into the place of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good, it will hold in any of them as well as the other:</hi> Grant this to be true, though it is of his own making; yet will this conclude, that whoever pleads Publick Good, Religion, or Reformation, is neceſſarily in the Right? And if it be ſo liable to be abuſed, Doth it not nearly concern us to examine well whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be not abuſed? When ſo many have been impoſed upon by it, and even we our ſelves ſo very lately almoſt to our utter Ruin, muſt we ſtill be ſuch Fools as to believe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out more adoe every bawling, or ſelf-intereſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Fellow, who cries <hi>Publick Good?</hi> For this Reaſon I did then fairly intimate, That <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good</hi> as a common Noiſe, or ſolitary Plea, is never to be admitted without ſuch <hi>Crite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rions,</hi> and other Evidences accompanying it, as may make it appear, that what is pleaded is real. And thus it will be in any of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes he ſuppoſeth; if he pleaſe he may ſet up the cry of <hi>Reformation,</hi> and then the Church of <hi>England</hi> is for Reforming the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> yea, at this time perhaps one part of it is for Reforming another; the Presbyterian would Reform them both, and the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:57050:13"/>
outdoeth him; and ſtill the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt hath a Knack of Reforming further, and the Quaker he is for Reforming them all. Now ſet all theſe on Work, and encourage them by telling them, That the Plea of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation being liable to be abuſed is no Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, but it is Inconſequent, and would reach to Publick Good, or any thing elſe; and if they were ſuffered to go on in this mad Humour, I am apt to think, that in a ſhort time, they would reform away all Religion. And if therefore Reformation be required, we muſt not preſently fall to altering or pulling down, but firſt enquire whether there be any thing that ſtands in need of Reformation. For if things be either well or near well, change is rarely for the better: But if there be diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red either ſuch groſs Errors, or intolerable A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes as need Reformation, yet it muſt be done in a regular Courſe; for though there ſhould be never ſo much need of Reformation, if you will allow all to be Publick Reformers, you will mend Religion worſe than thoſe Tinkers do Kettles, who, inſtead of ſtopping one hole, make two. And thus as to Publick Good, the bare Name of it is not enough, eſpecially when ſuch great Actions are pretended for the ſake of it, as for any thing we know may prove fatal; and therefore when ſuch a Pretence is ſet up, I think, there is a double Teſt where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it ought to be tryed; for as a Civil Society we ought to examine ſuch Pretences with their agreeableneſs to our Conſtitutions; for if they be contrary to them, they portend a Civil Deſtruction. But then as we are a Chriſtian Society, this Pretence of Publick Good muſt be examined by the Rules of Righteouſneſs, and the Goſpel of the Bleſſed Jeſus; and if Men will pretend for Publick Good, to diſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nul indiſpenſable Duties, to deſtroy all Faith and Truth amongſt Men, and to over-throw the very Nature of Good and Evil, by making it Changeable and Subſervient to every preſent Turn and Occaſion; this is the ready way to deſtroy not only the Civil Society, but the Chriſtian Church. And if that which makes void Promiſes and Oaths, which evacuates God's Commandments, which transforms Treachery into Vertue, and either makes it lawful to do Evil that Good may come of it, or flatly ſays it is no Evil, if Good may happen to come of it, (for I think there is not much Good come of it yet.) I ſay if this be not De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive of the Evangelical Rule, I know not what can. And if diſintereſſed Perſons were to judge of Particulars in the preſent Caſe, I dread to think on which Side even a Moral Heathen would give the Verdict, to the Shame of ſuch numbers of Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>The third thing propoſed, is, <hi>who ſhall be Judge?</hi> i. e. either of the Miſchief, or the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy. As to the former, he ſays, <hi>The Caſe before us is ſuppoſed to be notorious:</hi> It is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſuppoſed, but it was never proved. Muſt we deſtroy a King and Government for the Shams and Slanders that malicious Men ſuppoſe in defence of their Wickedneſs? Two things indeed he mentions, which have a Tendency (as he ſaith) to <hi>the Deſtruction of a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Deſertion and Lunacy.</hi> Now, if K. <hi>J.</hi> was Lunatick, this is the firſt time I have heard of it; but if he was, that is not a ſufficient ground to depoſe him: Indeed it may war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant the ſetting up a Protector, or Regent, to act in his Name; but the Honour and Title ſtill remain with him. This ſeems to be the Caſe of <hi>Edward</hi> III. who at the latter end of his Reign, being ſenſible of his Indiſpoſition for Government, made <hi>Lionel,</hi> Duke of <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> Regent of the Realm. But this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaved neither <hi>Edward</hi> III. his Father, nor <hi>Richard</hi> II. his Nephew, of their Right. As for Deſertion, I think they ought not for ſhame to have named it, unleſs they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned ſome better Anſwer to the Paper called <hi>Deſertion Diſcuſs'd,</hi> than impriſoning the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor. But he ſaith, I might as well have asked, <hi>who ſhall be the Judge, whether the Banks are broken down in an Inundation,</hi> &amp;c. I hope he doth not mean an Inundation of Foreigners, Poverty, and Cruelty. But who is it hath broke the Banks, or made the Breaches? Or how are they repared and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended? No doubt, but that now all is well, and we are out of danger, and as ſafe as Thieves in a Mill. But after all, he might have conſidered, That there is a great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between judging in Naturals and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks. As to the Objects of my Senſes, Nature hath made me the Judge, ſo that if I ſee the Water break in, or the Wall thrown down, I need not ask another, whether it be
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:57050:14"/>
ſo or no; but I am not ſo proper a Judge of the Tendency of my Superiours Actions, they being often moved by ſuch Springs as I cannot ſee, and therefore can make no certain Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them: And it is no ſtrange thing for People to miſtake theſe Actions when done, and not to know what is good for themſelves. Thus the Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> was accuſed for advancing Trade in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and for urging the neceſſity of the Interpoſition of the King's Authority, where the Letter of the Law was too ſevere upon his Subjects. And I could name the Perſon, who in Vindication of the Barbarity of the Kentiſh Men to a certain Perſon in Diſtreſs, urged his putting an Act in execution in thoſe parts, than which, ſcarce any thing more tended to the Advancement of our Trade, as even he, who urged it, had formerly acknowledged. Thus ſome people will make even Health it ſelf to be a Diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>Now, if we are not well qualified to judge of the Evil, we are ſtill more unfit to he judges of the Remedy. For it is a Madneſs to prate of applying a Cure to we know not what. But to put a ſtop here; he ſuppoſes Caſes wherein the Supreme Governour may be a Party, and therefore not to be allowed to be judge in his own Caſe; But then will not his Subjects be a Party too? And if they in this Caſe muſt be allowed to be Judge over the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Governour, What is this but to ſet a Supreme above a Supreme, whilſt he himſelf grants, <hi>That the Supreme Governour has no Supreme?</hi> But it is an idle if not a wicked Thing to ſuppoſe ſuch Caſes without proving them, when ſuch Suppoſals are made the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their Actions: For at this rate no Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment can be long-liv'd. When that is proved to be the Caſe, it is then time enough to diſcourſe of what may be done by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaties and Petitions of the People, and the Mediation of co-ordinate Powers, in order to ſet things to Rights. But let his Author ſay never ſo plainly, <hi>That he doth not ſet up the Power of the People over Kings,</hi> yet his Principles do; and Men act by thoſe, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they may pretend or ſay to the contrary.</p>
            <p>As to what concerns a <hi>Body of Men,</hi> he puts theſe two Queſtions from his Author. <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Law of our Nation doth not bind us to Allegiance to a King and Queen in actual Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Throne by conſent of the three Eſtates of th<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Realm? And whether ſuch an Oath may not lawfully be taken, notwithſtanding any former Oath?</hi> The affirmative he proves from <hi>the Conſent of the People, whoſe true Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives,</hi> (as he ſays) <hi>they are,</hi> I need not here examine of what Force is the Conſent of the People, becauſe the Foundation whereon he Grounds it, as to our preſent Caſe, is falſe: For the three Eſtates of the Realm are the King's three Eſtates, and they can neither be legal Eſtates, nor legal Repreſentatives with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the King's Authority, Writs, and Summons, and other Requiſites. But, it ſeems, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirer here put an unlucky Queſtion. <hi>Where or how can all the People meet?</hi> Which he ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully thus Anſwers. <hi>As if the Author he op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes thought of no leſs than the numbering of the People from</hi> Dan <hi>to</hi> Beerſheba. But if he did not think of numbering them from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Beerſheba,</hi> he ought to have thought of numbering them from <hi>Barwick</hi> to <hi>Dover.</hi> For if the Government was not diſſolved, Why goes it not according to the Conſtitution? If it was diſſolved, than all Men were as free as it is poſſible for Men to be; and then no Man could repreſent another without his expreſs Conſent; and every ones Conſent ought to be taken <hi>Viritim;</hi> for whoſoever did not give his Conſent, did not come into your new Body, and his natural Freedom could not without Injuſtice be taken from him by Force.</p>
            <p>When I thought we had been near an end, he is got again to the begining; and when he was <hi>thinking of cloſing,</hi> in the very next Words, he propounds no leſs than three Heads of Diſcourſe, which, he ſays, his <hi>Author trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of towards the begining;</hi> but all amount to no more, but the old Cuckoo Note of Publick Good, and that it ought to over-rule every thing; as to which I might briefly An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That Publick Good is to be promoted in the way of Duty, not out of it; and this is very ill taken up for a Plea, where there is neither Publick Good nor Duty in the Matter they plead for. But he undertakes to prove the Matter by Inſtances, only they are Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which have been already Anſwered, and he doth not handle them ſo dexterouſly as his Author. He begins with Parents and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deren, and unlucky Omen: <hi>If</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a Vow
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:57050:14"/>
to God (which is as ſolemn a Thing as an Oath) hinders that good, which Children are bound to do to Parents, it ceaſeth to oblige as our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our declares:</hi> Very good. But the reaſon is, becauſe that Vow never obliged at all, as be-ing unlawful, and contrary to that which God and Nature had made a Duty of Childeren to Parents, though Wicked or Froward. I thought the Duty of Children to Parents had been Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated; at leaſt, Sir, you ought to have over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look'd it. But I deſire it may be obſerved, That, to make amends for this overſight, this very Author, who here makes the Duty of Childeren to Parents ſo Sacred that it makes void a Vow to God himſelf, within 3 Pages next following teacheth you a trick to vacate the Obligation of the Fifth Commandment.</p>
            <p>But it ſeems I had ſaid, That this was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the purpoſe, and I think I there pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it: But he ſays, <hi>it is to the purpoſe,</hi> becauſe <hi>if the procuring and preſerving the Publick Good be a Duty, and what a Perſon hath vowed or ſworn be deſtructive of it, then the Oath cannot oblige, no more than a Vow,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>(p.</hi> 28.) But I ſay this alſo is nothing to the Purpoſe. For though the procuring and preſerving the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good be a Duty, yet it doth not make every thing a Duty, which may tend towards it; and it muſt be procured and preſerved only by means lawful and honeſt. If Children might murther their Parents for the Publick Good, ſuch Parents as have large Eſtates and wicked Children, had need look out ſharp; for Pretences, even of Publick Good, would not long be wanting to ſend them of an Errand to another World.</p>
            <p>Whereas I had ſaid, with reſpect to ſuch Oath or Vow, That <hi>the Sin was in making,</hi> &amp;c. he ſays this is true, <hi>where the Matter is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful in it ſelf,</hi> but not where <hi>the Obligation comes to ceaſe.</hi> And this I grant alſo to be true; but then a Man ought to be very well aſſured that the Obligation doth ceaſe, for otherwiſe all the Arts and Shifts in the world will not abſolve him from Perjury. And I inſiſted on the firſt, as being our Caſe; and therefore his Inſtance of the <hi>Shew-bread</hi> is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the Matter: For though, as dedicated to God, it belonged to the Prieſts, yet it was never unlawful in it ſelf for a Man to eat Bread; nor did ſuch Dedication hinder the Prieſts from being Charitable, and in caſe of neceſſity, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving a good Man from being ſtarved. And though it he the faſhion of our days, not only to make Men poor, but by all means poſſible to hinder them from any Relief, that they may ſtarve; yet he needed not to have gone to the <hi>Jews</hi> for an Inſtance, but might have told us of Chriſtian Biſhops, who in times of Famine have ſold the Riches of their Churches, to buy Food for the Poor; and Poſterity hath ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured their Memory for it. As for his Story of <hi>Jaddus,</hi> I will not trouble my ſelf to call it in queſtion; it will be ſomewhat to the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe when he can prove theſe three things, 1. That <hi>Jaddus</hi> and the <hi>Jews</hi> took an Oath to <hi>Alexander:</hi> I find no ſuch thing in the Story; and he knows that we do not deny all manner of Submiſſion to Force. 2. That <hi>Darius</hi> was living when <hi>Jaddus</hi> made the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. 3. That we have the ſame Authority, Warrant, and Directions, which <hi>Jaddus</hi> and the <hi>Jews</hi> had; as to which laſt, he may do very well to addreſs himſelf to a certain Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, whom he very well knows, and try if he can find it in the <hi>Revelations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next Inſtance is of <hi>the Parents Part to Children,</hi> as to which he cites theſe words from his Author; <hi>If Parents, inſtead of regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Good of their Children, do openly deſign their Ruine, none will ſay but that they are bound to take Care of their own Wellfare.</hi> They are ſo; but yet even then there is a Duty owing from thoſe Children to thoſe Parents. But in order to take off my Anſwer there given, as if he had received a double Portion of <hi>Hugh Peters</hi>'s Spirit, he falls to his black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ening Arts, and with the help of Flam-Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals and notorious Falſhoods, repreſents as indulgent a Father as perhaps lived, as if he were another <hi>Saturn,</hi> who devoured his own Iſſue; and then he thinks the Child <hi>may enter upon the Eſtate, and keep Poſſeſſion againſt his Parent,</hi> &amp;c. and then tryumphantly asks this queſtion, <hi>May not all this be done, and the Fifth Commandment ſtand in its full Force?</hi> Yes, Sir! the Fifth Commandment will be in force, and you and others, ſome time or other, will find ſo; but as you order the Matter here, you make it either of no Force, or of Force to very ill purpoſe; for ſo I take it to be, when it lays no other Obligation upon the Child,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:57050:15"/>
but to diſpoſſeſs the Father of his Eſtate, or to knock out his Brains. Do not you think you have done an Heroick Act, thus to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute away the fifth Cammannment? But at this rate, I am afraid you will paint <hi>White-Chapel</hi> black, and make People doubtful, how he is a Preacher of Righteouſneſs, who deviſes Tricks to take away the Obl<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gation of God's Commandments.</p>
            <p>The third Inſtance is of <hi>Maſters and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, Victors and Captives; and in theſe</hi> (his Author ſays) <hi>there is a Regard had to the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of thoſe, who are in Subjection.</hi> This I did grant, but withall deny, That any Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence could be drawn thence, which would be for his turn. But here he accuſeth me of Ignorance, Nonſenſe, Blunders, and what not, and all along after ſpeaks in ſuch inſolent lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, as I think is only fit to be deſpiſed; and therefore I will not do him the Pleaſure to take any farther notice of it: Only I think it diſingenuous to cite my Words by the halves, and then cry out of <hi>Nonſenſe and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtencies.</hi> But it was impudence, aſſoon as this was done, to repeat the following Words, which both make them Senſe, and take away all Inconſiſtency. But to my Argument he anſwers, <hi>That being under Government (rightly ſo called,) doth not Metamorphoſe us into Beaſts; yet mere abſolute Power comes very near it.</hi> I know not what he means by his <hi>Government (rightly ſo called;)</hi> I hope it is not Uſurpation. That Parentheſis would better have become another, than him. But his Anſwer is neither to the purpoſe, nor true: For there neither is nor can be any Government, but ſomewhere there is lodg'd in it that, which he calls <hi>an abſolute Power;</hi> and thus in his way of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing, he hath near <hi>Metamorphoſed</hi> all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind into Beaſts, unleſs there be any ſuch as are under no Government at all. I as hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily wiſh, as he or any other Man can, That Power may be well uſed; and yet I think I ought to be content to allow my Governours their Failings, without mutinying againſt them, and diſplacing them: This would be, not only endleſs, but to condemn our ſelves; for if it were ſaid to us, <hi>he that is without Sin, let him caſt the firſt ſtone,</hi> I doubt you would ſcarce find one to begin the Work. His Diſtinction of a <hi>private Injury</hi> from that <hi>wherein the Publick is concerned,</hi> is not practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable upon his Principle: For let it be made lawful on any account to depoſe the ſupream Governour, and the leaſt and moſt private In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury imaginable ſhall be interpreted a Breach of the Subjects Privilege in general, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently againſt the Publick Good. But there will be no need for this, according to his Principle. For if the <hi>antecedent Good</hi> (as he calls it) <hi>be ſo the Meaſure of the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as to diſſolve it,</hi> when that is wanting, every Man will be prone to think his own particular Good to be as much that antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Good, as any thing he can call publick; and conſequently if he be wronged, will take himſelf to be abſolved from his Allegiance. This is an admirable way to make Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment firm and ſtable.</p>
            <p>The laſt Relation he mentions is between Princes and their Subjects, as to which, the only material thing he ſays, is, <hi>That the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Political Oaths is ſuch, that they are reciprocal.</hi> Now though I do not think this will hold, yet to what purpoſe ſhould I enter into a Diſcourſe about Oaths, when our Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs is with the Duties, which were antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the Oaths, and to the Performance of which we are more ſtrongly bound by thoſe Oaths! Theſe undoubtedly are not recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal: For if the Subject will not do his Duty, or abſolutely deny it, doth this deprive the King of his Right to Sovereignty? At this rate indeed we may depoſe Kings, and trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Allegiance at pleaſure. It were a very happy thing, if the Duties of Relations were always juſtly and mutually paid; but if there be (as too often there is) a Failure on the one part, it doth not diſcharge the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the other. Children owe a Duty to wicked Parents, Servants to hard Maſters, Subjects to ſevere Kings; though it were much better, if they had more Encouragement to perform their Obligations.</p>
            <p>Every Cur will be ſnarling at the dead Lyon, whom otherwiſe he durſt not look in the Face. The Actions, Writings, and Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> were enough to blaſt theſe Proceedings; and therefore almoſt every Scribler for the late Treachery doth all he can to leſſen their Eſteem in the World. I had particular occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:57050:15"/>
to vindicate Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon;</hi> but he tells me I miſtake between <hi>what the Conſent of the abſent Prince is founded upon, and upon what the Caſuiſts found their Opinion of the Obligation that lies on Mankind to do what tends to the Publick Good under a <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation;</hi> and this he calls teaching me <hi>A. B. C.</hi> and indeed I think he is much fitter to teach <hi>A. B. C.</hi> than ſo great a Congregation, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he had more Conſcience and Honeſty. However, I will not learn my <hi>A. B. C.</hi> of him, if it were only for this Reaſon, that I have no mind to learn it backward. But if he pleaſe to look into his Author again, with a more impartial Eye, he will find that he invidiouſly and maliciouſly endeavours to charge and undervalue Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> as founding the Actions of Subjects under a Uſurpation on ſuch a Reaſon as other Caſuiſts did not; and as if he made the preſumptive Will of the Prince the ſole Reaſon: And in this Caſe, I think I had Reaſon to urge, That he founded the preſumptive Conſent of the Prince upon the Publick Good; and I ſhall not willingly ſuffer ſo great a Perſon to be ſcandalized, let him put his <hi>B</hi>'s and <hi>C</hi>'s how he will.</p>
            <p>The laſt Head he propounds is <hi>of Obedience to Authority,</hi> which if it had been more thought of, and better obſerved, there had been no occaſion to diſpute about it now: And I wonder with what face thoſe Men can name <hi>Obedience to Authority,</hi> who make it their whole Buſineſs to juſtifie Diſobedience to Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. Here, after ſome little Wit, and much trifling, and the Charge of ſome Miſtakes upon me, which I think might be eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, but I will not ſpend time about it, becauſe they come not up to the Caſe; at laſt he replies to my Anſwer concerning the Caſe of the <hi>Jews:</hi> And this is the only thing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial he offers under this Head. My firſt Anſwer, <hi>That the Jews being governed by one of their own Brethren was deſigned as a Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, the contrary was a Judgment,</hi> he doth not deny: But he would thence infer this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, <hi>That therefore they might not lawfully transfer their Allegiance from their own Blood to a Foreigner.</hi> And this he thinks he can prove falſe. But I do not know how that Conſequence follows from my Words. The <hi>Jews</hi> ſpontaniouſly, wantonly, and by their own Authority, could not transfer their Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance; but when God, for their Sins, depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them of a particular Privilege and Bleſſing, and put them under the Power of others, and they knew it was his Will it ſhould be ſo; they were then bound to obey. And thus <hi>Nehemiah</hi> might ſerve as <hi>Governour under</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxerxes, <hi>and</hi> Jaddus <hi>take an Oath of Fidelity to</hi> Darius. And hence you ſee on <hi>what Right the Oath was founded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next I urged, that they were under a ſtate of Conqueſt, this he doth neither deny, nor own it to be our Caſe; and unleſs he doth this latter, whatever he infers thence, whether true or falſe, cannot affect us. And therefore I am not further concerned to anſwer a Man, who labours to make acts of Violence to be ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Rules for all Seaſons.</p>
            <p>In the third place I did (as he ſays) urge, <hi>That the Queſtion to our Saviour was not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Oaths, but Tribute, which he grants all Caſuiſts do allow may be paid, even to an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper.</hi> But then he ſays, <hi>I know what <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe, and what Gain too, my Adverſary made of this.</hi> But if he made an ill Uſe of it, how can I help it? Muſt I Anſwer for that? As for his Gain, if he mean a Biſhoprick, it is ſomething; but as to the Merits of the Cauſe I cannot ſee, that he hath Gained any thing. But after all, both the Uſe an Gain, is an Argument borrowed from Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> which runs to this purpoſe; if Submiſſion may be teſtified one way, why not another? If Tribute may be paid, why not promiſed? If promiſed, why not ſworn? And then he asks, <hi>Is it not as a Token of Allegeance?</hi> The Anſwer is plain. I may ſubmit wherein it may be done lawfully, but not wherein it is unlawful. I may pay Money to a Thief, I may promiſe it, yea ſuch may be my Streights and Dangers, that I may ſwear to do it; and yet this is not as a Token of Allegiance, which all that time is due to my King, and ought not to be made over to a Thief; it is the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of my Life, or Goods, and the chooſing a leſs Evil rather than a greater in a caſe, wherein I may do it without Sin. For in ſuch caſe, I think, I may lawfully part with my own, though it is unlawful for the other to take it. And if this Anſwer will not pleaſe him, he may ſtill call me Fool, as he
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:57050:16"/>
here doth; I like the Title much better than Knave, though I am fond of neither.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, With reſpect to <hi>Tiberius</hi> it was urged, that no Man had <hi>jus potius,</hi> and that there was no prior Oaths in bar againſt him; as to which he Anſwers, That <hi>Agrippa Poſthumus was then living, one much nearer to</hi> Auguſtus, <hi>and that ſeem'd deſigned by him to ſucceed him.</hi> What he means by <hi>ſeem'd deſigned</hi> I cannot tell. Was he really deſigned, or not? It is a common thing for Relations to waver in their Thoughts, which way they ſhall beſtow their Favours, and ſometimes it is a piece of Art; but if <hi>Tiberius was deſigned</hi> (as he calls it) <hi>at laſt,</hi> the Cauſe is ſo far caſt. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this will not do, he ſays, That <hi>there was a</hi> jus potius <hi>in the Senate, from whom even</hi> Auguſtus <hi>was willing to receive it.</hi> But if <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> who was before <hi>Tiberius,</hi> did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Senates Right, then their Right was gone before <hi>Tiberius</hi>'s time, and ſo the <hi>jus po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> is good on his ſide ſtill. Beſide by their own Laws they might make a Dictator, and they had actually made <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Dictator, who was before them both, and in that very act gave away their Power; ſo that their giving up to <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> was but Selling their Eſtate twice. And after all, his Author confeſſes they ſwore Allegiance to <hi>Tiberius;</hi> and where was then their <hi>jus po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius?</hi> As to the prior Oaths he asks me, <hi>What I think of the Oath of</hi> Jaddus <hi>to</hi> Darius, <hi>&amp;c.?</hi> And in requital I ask him again, What is that in bar to the Title of <hi>Tiberius?</hi> So that if <hi>Tiberius</hi> was as bad a Man as he repreſents him, (and indeed I never thought him a Saint, though for his Art in Diſſimulation he might have been qualified for one in theſe times) yet in ſpite of our Author his Title will prove the beſt he can ſet up.</p>
            <p>As to the better Title, which he ſaith he <hi>will adventure to ſet before me,</hi> he may keep it to himſelf; he hath offered his Ware to a wrong Chapman: But for his Kindneſs I will leave him this Remark, That when the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> forſook the living God to worſhip Graven Images, the greater part were always more zealous for their Idols than for the true God.</p>
            <p>In the Concluſion I find, that our Author is ſupoſitions of the force of his Arguments; for he will not leave me to <hi>the Tribunal of Heaven,</hi> but threatens me with being <hi>called to account here,</hi> and I do not queſtion but that he will do his endeavour, nor do I crave any Favour at his Hands. He that calls me to Sufferings, I hope will enable me to bear them; and in ſuch caſe I have no other Remedy, but to appeal to the juſt God, before whom one Day we ſhall have a Rehearing. And when it comes to my Thoughts how a Turk at <hi>Buda,</hi> laying his Hand on his Breſt, promiſed not to yield up the Town but with his Life, and in purſuance of his Word ſo Manfully defended it, that it coſt a victorious Army dear, and took up almoſt two Summers Work, and when the Place was Untenable any longer might have made honourable Conditions, yet rather than break his Promiſe, choſe to ſtand in the Breach, in his Drawers, and tempt and deſie Death; it amazeth me to think, who ſhall riſe up in Judgment againſt this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous and Perfidious Generation. <hi>O God of Goodneſs and Compaſſion! in the midſt of Judgment think on Mercy, have Pity upon this poor diſtreſſed Church, and give Men a Senſe of that Simplicity, Sincerity, and Integrity, which thy Law ſo highly extols and ſtrictly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of all who call themſelves Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:57050:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
